<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A defense against the dread of death, or, Zach. Crofton's meditations and soliloquies concerning the stroak of death sounded in his ears in the time of his close imprisonment in the Tower of London, anno 1661 and 1662 : digested for his own private staisfaction and support in the vale of the shadow of death, and now made publique for the advantage of such as abide under Gods present visitation in London by the pestilence.</title>
            <author>Crofton, Zachary, 1625 or 6-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1665</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 177 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 89 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35042</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6992</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24795</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08495943</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08495943</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41414</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35042)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41414)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1253:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A defense against the dread of death, or, Zach. Crofton's meditations and soliloquies concerning the stroak of death sounded in his ears in the time of his close imprisonment in the Tower of London, anno 1661 and 1662 : digested for his own private staisfaction and support in the vale of the shadow of death, and now made publique for the advantage of such as abide under Gods present visitation in London by the pestilence.</title>
                  <author>Crofton, Zachary, 1625 or 6-1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 160 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1665.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Death --  Meditations.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41414:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41414:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>DEFENCE Againſt the Dread of Death, OR, <hi>ZACH. CROFTON'S</hi> Meditations and Soliloquies concerning the ſtroak of death ſounded in his ears, in the time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his cloſe Impriſonment in the <hi>Tow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of <hi>London, Anno.</hi> 1661, and 166<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>Digeſted for his own private ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſupport in the vale of the ſhadow of death.</p>
            <p>AND NOW Made publique for the advantage of ſuch as abide under Gods preſent Viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in <hi>London</hi> by the Peſtilence.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:41414:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41414:2"/>
            <head>To the ſerious dying Chriſtian Reader; Eſpecially thoſe in and about <hi>London;</hi> ſubjected to Gods vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation by the preſent Peſtilence; and under a daily exſpectation of an arreſt by death.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian and beloved Friends.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat was lately mine, is now become your ſad eſtate; <hi>viz. the dreadful expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of deaths ſtroak;</hi> in the multitude of my thoughts within me, the conſolations of God did refreſh and revive my ſoul: the kind of death w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> threatned me, is different from what impendeth you; but the object of dread was to me and you the ſame, <hi>(viz) Death:</hi> and the ſame apprehenſions of its nature which did affect me, muſt affect you with <hi>fear</hi> and <hi>hope:</hi> the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing meditations miniſtred a check to my paſſions, and comfort to my ſpirit; by theſe, I perſwaded my ſoul to be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and contented, though not deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb facs="tcp:41414:3"/>to part from my body; and to let me cheerfully lye down and dye: theſe were digeſted on my perſonal account; for my private ſupport and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment under the fears of death: they having done their work were by me con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to death, at least to preſent darkneſs, but are now by your ſad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition animated, and reſtored; and the publication thereof is extorted by the importunity of ſome ſpecial friends who had formerly ſeen and peruſed them; and in an affectionate ſence of your ſad condition ſubjected to the <hi>terrors of night;</hi> the <hi>Arrow which flyeth by day;</hi> the <hi>Peſtilence which walketh in darkneſs,</hi> and <hi>the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction which waſteth at noon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day:</hi> calling more loudly for Antidotes to the ſting, then to the ſtroak of death; have reſtleſly ſollicited theſe papers to be put into your hands.</p>
            <p>The dread of death is as common, as natural to man; as is the ſtroak thereof: it never appeared with its pale face, to any ſubject of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ht
<pb facs="tcp:41414:3"/>reaſon or true religion; but with a terrifying aſpect: the Heathen accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it, <hi>of terrible things the moſt terrible;</hi> they could no way render it comfortable; but by repreſenting it the ſum, the completion, and ſo the period of evil and miſery: Cold comfort! The Scripture calleth it the <hi>King of terrors:</hi> which of Gods Saints have not feared to dye? <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> was beſet with the <hi>terrors of death: Paul</hi> could not deſire to be <hi>unclothed:</hi> The onely begotten Son of God, had his ſoul <hi>heavy unto death,</hi> and in a fearful agony depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated the ſtroak thereof: the Saints never curſed the day of their birth, and cryed out for their death; but in the extremity of their perplexity, and in the prevalency of their paſſion; evidenced by this very character: men exempt from phrenſie; and not mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſly, extraordinarily acted by a divine ſpirit, as were <hi>the three Children,</hi> and other <hi>Martyrs:</hi> muſt be the ſubjects of ſtoical Apa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie,
<pb facs="tcp:41414:4"/>ſenſeleſs ſtupidity, ſtrong de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions, or a reprobate ſenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, if they fear not the ſtroak of death: I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy not ſome (who hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I thought dyed too ſtoutly in ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h a cauſe) their courage and con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>dence in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facing death: But this I muſt ſay to all; <hi>Chriſtianun agere,</hi> is not, <hi>hominem exucre: Chriſtians ceaſe not to be men, nor is it fit they ſhould ſo do. Bernard</hi> well noteth of <hi>Peter</hi> the Apoſtle,
<note place="margin">Bernardi Tract. de gratia &amp; Libero Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrio.</note> that his ſin was not in the ſimple fear of death, <hi>Mortem evadere voluit; quid iſtud criminis fuit? voluit mori; inculpabilis eſt:</hi> To be unwilling, affraid to dye, is lawfully humane, and not blame-worthy in a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an: It is equally monſtrous in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and a judgement from the Lord not to <hi>fear to dye:</hi> and <hi>not to mourn for the dead.</hi> I muſt ſay with the holy <hi>Greenham, They are as well to be liked who fear death, as thoſe who joy at it:</hi> And I for my part fluctuating on the waves of
<pb facs="tcp:41414:4"/>violence and uncertainty, in an evil age and world; muſt ſay as this good man,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Greenh. work.</hi> p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Notwithſtanding my many croſſes which hinder the comfort of my life; I do not, I dare not deſire to die.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Death is in its nature moſt terrify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſoul; yet its dreadful cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances and concomitants do ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily more affect the ſence, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke the paſſions. <hi>Seneca</hi> placed the moſt dread in the Scaffold the Ax, the attendance, the ſpectators, the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners, and march to execution, that <hi>pompa mortis:</hi> Theſe were no meanly affecting circumſtances to me in my expectation of a violent death; to you the ſuddenneſs, the ſolitarineſs, the certainty of the ſtroak, by an inevita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble noiſom contagion, may appear moſt grievous. He who dieth in due courſe of nature, meeteth with dread in death; but he that dieth by ſome ſpecial kind of death, as by ſword or peſtilence hath his dread aggravated; and more eminently needeth the defence of a
<pb facs="tcp:41414:5"/>lively faith, to repel the terrors of a lively ſence, which can and muſt be the reſult of a rational and Chriſtian apprehenſion of deaths changed na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and quality, with the ſequels thereof through Chriſt the Lord of life; theſe will alleviate the burden, abate the ſtrength, abſtract the ſting, and alter the countenance of death; of any kind of death.</p>
            <p>Familiarity breedeth contempt, and caſteth out fear: the Fox by fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quency playeth boldly with the lion. We read of an <hi>Hungarian</hi> Prince, who affected his youthful brother, rebuked his daily meditations of death, with an unexpected ſummons to executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Men little think of dying there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are the terrors of death ſo ſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>Plato</hi> perſwading to thoughts of death,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> defined <hi>true Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy</hi> to be a <hi>meditation of death:</hi> Certain it is, that they who will truly Chriſtianize, muſt be much in conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of death; and careful to dye well. When men are every moment
<pb facs="tcp:41414:5"/>obnoxious to the ſudden and certain ſtroaks of death, it is time (if ever they will be wiſe) to labour to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent death lovely to their ſouls: fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Sermons <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ound beſt in the ears; ſpectacles of mortality is the moſt pleaſing ſight; and meditations of death the moſt delighting ſtudy, not only to the mortified Chriſtian, but alſo to the dying man. <hi>Croeſus</hi> the rich King of <hi>Lydia,</hi> when captivated, ſtript, and tyed alive to the ſtake which muſt make his funeral pile; could affectionately cry out, <hi>O So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, Solon!</hi> and preach to <hi>Cyrus</hi> his Conqueror <hi>Solons Dictates of Mortality,</hi> which in his proſperity he had deſpiſed. And <hi>Seneca</hi> decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in <hi>Neroes</hi> favour, and drawing nigh to his violent death, did best diſcern, and moſt clearly declare that mans felicity was after death. The prophane men, which in health neglect and deſpiſe Gods Miniſters, and cannot endure to hear of death, or Jeſus Chriſt; can on a ſick bed
<pb facs="tcp:41414:6"/>ſend for them, gladly hear the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of Mortality; and cry out I muſt die, <hi>O Chiſt ſave me! O Chriſt ſave me!</hi> Nor is it mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell for every <hi>Balaam</hi> ready to curſe Gods <hi>Iſrael</hi> on the ſence of deaths appraach, cannot but wiſh to die the <hi>death of the righteous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I would willingly hope, thoſe who have now the charge of your ſouls, are tender of you as Nurſes, and careful for you as Parents; and that with due affection and fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity they labour to fit you for, and encourage you under the ſtroaks of death: Never (I am ſure) had you more need: never were you more likely to hear the Charmer, and to receive inſtruction, then in ſo ſad a day of viſitation from the Lord. I wiſh I were without any grounds of fear to the contrary. I lately travelling about my ruſtick affairs, met many Miniſters from your City, among other Citizens, withdrawing from that place of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger:
<pb facs="tcp:41414:6"/>their receſs I could not but obſerve with grief and anger; think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing who muſt miniſter to you ghoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly councel, now your ſouls are in the ſhadow of death; how must it ſting your ſerious hearts to ſee your <hi>lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers</hi> and <hi>friends</hi> ſtand at a diſtance, and your <hi>Prophets all gone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am not ſo uncharitable as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the receſs of any, not ſpecially bound to ſtay in infected places, to be ſin: I beleive men that flye from the Peſtilence, are no more Atheiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, or to be blamed as ſuch, then thoſe who flye from the Sword: I judge the receſs of many, may be a prudential ſerving of Gods provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, unto the withdrawing of the contagion, naturally communicating it ſelf in vicinity: but, I cannot but judge <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> to keep order; <hi>Phyſitians</hi> to help nature; and <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> to prepare for and encourage againſt death are bound to ſtay, and in the diſcharge of their duty to truſt God with their lives.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:41414:7"/>
            <p>I cannot ſecure Miniſters their lives in contagious places; I well know that Hiſtories tells us ſome of <hi>the Miniſters and Deacons which miniſtred to the Saints in Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſeb. Hiſt. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 22.</note> in the great Plague which there raged, dyed thereof: And that the Families of <hi>Bullinger,</hi> and <hi>Beza</hi> were herewith infected, yet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves eſcaped, and were preſerved; yet God hath ordinarily ſaved the lives of thoſe who in love to immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſouls, have adventured to looſe them: Mr. <hi>Sam. Fiſher,</hi> whoſe meditation on death in the time of the Plague in <hi>Salop,</hi> we have pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique among us; is yet alive to tell unto Gods praiſe, how himſelf, and Reverend Mr. <hi>Blake</hi> were preſerved in their Miniſtration to that place, in the time of a raging Peſtilence: If deſpiſed I might be ſo bold, I would deſire your preſent Miniſters, to conſider the late Biſhop <hi>Halls</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in this very caſe; he having juſtified the rece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f private perſons;
<pb facs="tcp:41414:7"/>thus conculdeth concerning Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; <hi>You urge the inſtance of your Miniſters, how unequally,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bp. <hi>Halls Epiſt. Dec.</hi> 4. <hi>Ep.</hi> 9.</note> 
               <hi>there is not more lawfulneſs in your flight, then ſin in ours: you are your own, we are our peoples: you are charged with a body which you may not willingly loſe, nor hazard by ſtaying: we with all their ſouls, which to hazard by our abſence, is to loſe our own: we muſt love our lives, but not when they are rivals with our ſouls, or with others: how much better is it to be dead, then negligent? then faithleſs? if ſome bodies be contagiouſly ſick, ſhall all ſouls be neglected? to run away from a neceſſary and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique good, to avoid a doubtful and private evil, is to run into a worſe evil then that we would avoid, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whilſt worthleſs I am dead as to my Miniſtry, I hope I may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live as to my Meditations: And
<pb facs="tcp:41414:8"/>freely by an harmleſs Pen Miniſter them to you; eſpecially on a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject ſo innocent, ſo neceſſary as is <hi>Death;</hi> Its <hi>Dread,</hi> and the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence againſt it:</hi> I beſeech you receive theſe as miniſterial ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the good of your ſouls: they were indeed onely ſpoken to my dying ſelf: Put your ſouls in my ſouls ſtead, and they will ſpeak to you: the ſpecial kind of death which I dreaded, may make ſome things ſeem improper to your preſent ſtate; but the general matter and ſcope of them, is to <hi>obviate death,</hi> as ſuch in its gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral nature; and ſo they are appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable to any kind of death: I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you prepare your ſelves to dye, and thereby perſwade your ſouls to be willing to dye: you and I muſt dye, it mattereth not what kind of death we dye: be we careful to dye <hi>in the Lord,</hi> and <hi>for the Lord:</hi> ſo ſhall death conſummate our miſery, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigh
<pb facs="tcp:41414:8"/>our fouls into the fulneſs of felicity. <hi>Auſtin</hi> well noteth, <hi>Quid intereſt an Febris</hi> (Let us ſay <hi>Peſtis) an ferrum nos de corpore ſolverit? noli qua occaſione,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. Epiſt.</hi> 122. <hi>ad victori.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſed quales ad ſe exeant, domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus attendit inſervis ſuis: It mattereth not whether Sword or Plague kill us:</hi> Saints are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to any, to every of them: God doth more regard the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of his Dying Servants, then the means of their death: the change of quality in us, chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the quality of death unto us.</p>
            <p>Now that God may fit you for death, familiarize to you that King of fears; fix your ſouls on Chriſt, who is <hi>life in death:</hi> and ſo fill your hearts with thoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, which may prevail with you to dye willingly, untill he pleaſe to accept an attonement: and call back the deſtroying An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel
<pb facs="tcp:41414:9"/>is and ſhall be the moſt affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and conſtant prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours in the Lord, fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the good of you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſouls, whilſt he is,</hi> Z. C.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>July <hi>20<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 1665.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41414:9"/>
            <head>A DEFENCE Againſt the Dread of DEATH; OR, <hi>Z. C.</hi> his ſerious Soliloquies, and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations of Death; under the alarms thereof, ſounded in the time of his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment in the Tower of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, An.</hi> 1661.</head>
            <div type="preface">
               <head>The PREFACE.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He wrath of the King, is the meſſenger of death; O ſad meſſenger! O evil tidings! what is more unwelcome to man? what is more diſtaſteful to nature? can it chuſe but diſmay my ſoul, and affect my ſpirit? is not Death that, which
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41414:10"/>nature hath determined to be of <hi>Terrible</hi> things the moſt <hi>Terrible?</hi> doth not the Scripture denominate it,
<note place="margin">Job 18.14</note> 
                  <hi>The King of Terrors?</hi> doth not the ſence of death daunt the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of the ſtouteſt men of War? damp the comforts of this World? doth not this diſcompoſe the moſt compoſed Chriſtian, and moſt ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Saint? were not the <hi>ſnares,</hi> the <hi>ſorrows,</hi> the <hi>ſhade</hi> of <hi>Death,</hi> the things which <hi>David</hi> (that good, that ſtout man) did ſo paſſionately be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wail,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 18.4, 5. &amp; 116.3.</note> and pray to be delivered from? the fear of Death made upright <hi>Hezekiah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 38.</note> 
                  <hi>To chatter like a Crane, and mourn like a Swallow;</hi> The Devil well knew what he ſaid,
<note place="margin">Job 2.4.</note> when he ſaid, <hi>All that a man hath he would give for his life:</hi> The Lord of life entred not the Liſt, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter Death, without an <hi>heavy ſpirit;</hi> he needed ſome comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble companions to watch with him under this conflict; he was not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to profeſs, <hi>My ſoul is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41414:10"/>ſorrowful unto death;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 26.38, 39.</note> and once, again, and a third time to pray, <hi>Father, if it be poſſible, let this cup paſs from me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Shall I exſpect to be <hi>exempt from;</hi> Shall I be afraid or aſhamed to <hi>expreſs</hi> the paſſions which were exiſtent in all Gods Saints, and from which my Lord and Maſter himſelf was not freed? I am a Chriſtian, but yet a man; I am a Miniſter, but yet a man; if I dye, as I now fear, I dye inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently; Lord thou knoweſt I dye for righteouſneſs ſake; I ſhall be a Martyr, though of the loweſt orbe; this may mitigate dread; but it maketh no change in me, or in death, yet terrors attend it, and paſſions abide in me. The moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved <hi>Paul,</hi> was ſo far from being aſhamed,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.8, 9.</note> that he was deſirous the Church ſhould know <hi>he was preſſed above meaſure;</hi> when he deſpaired of life, and received in himſelf the ſentence of death,
<note place="margin">and 5.4.</note> the moſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41414:11"/>deſirous to be cloathed with their <hi>Houſe from Heaven,</hi> could never yet deſire to be uncloathed of their <hi>earthly Tabernacle;</hi> nature can be much more content to be changed, then to dye.</p>
               <p>Death draweth me out of the boſome of the Wife of my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light; divideth me from my Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, the glory of my youth; driveth me from my Kindred, Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, Friends, and all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſociety; Can I part from theſe with dry eyes? can men think I bear to theſe a natural af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and expect I ſhould bid adiew to them, not affected with natural paſſion? doth nature and religion direct me to love them? and will they not allow me to grieve when I leave them?</p>
               <p>Death doth diſcapacitate me for the ſervice of my God and his Church; the grave cannot praiſe him; Death cannot celebrate him; They who go down into the pit
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41414:11"/>cannot hope for his truth; will not Chriſtianity, true Piety, teach me with dread to diſcern this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate? am I perſwaded my life is more profitable for the Church? can I then avoid St. <hi>Pauls ſtrait?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 1, 21, 22, 23, 24.</note> and be eaſily reſolved what to chooſe; though to me it is <hi>more profitable that I dye?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Death doth deſtroy my being; when I am dead I am not; can diſſolution chooſe but dictate dread to ſenſible, much more to rational beings?</p>
               <p>Death is the wages of ſin; the witneſs of Gods wrath; and the curſe of the Law, and by its cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances made ſuch with an em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaſis; can then a man of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, receive the ſame without reluctancy and great remorſe?</p>
               <p>Death is the inlet of mine im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal ſoul, into the Ocean of eternity; can I apprehend it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out amazement, and great aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment?</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:41414:12"/>
               <p>Let malefactours outface; out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dare this King of dread; and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to themſelves the name and honour of Martyrs, by their only abandoning the fear of death; I dare not imitate, I muſt not juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, I cannot, I will not follow them; theſe fig-leaves will not hide their ſin from the face of God.</p>
               <p>My ſoul! keep thy paſſions with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in bounds, then fear not to give them vent; and to expreſs the ſame before God and Men; <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibile eſt hominem exuere;</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity doth not require thee to turn ſtoick, and ceaſe to be a man; Let the fear <hi>of Gods caſting thee into hell,</hi> have the prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence; then ceaſe not to fear <hi>mens killing thy body;</hi> ſell not thy ſelf, to ſave a natural life; and then ſpare nothing to redeem the ſame from death; by the exception of this one thing <hi>thy ſelf,</hi> make the Devil a liar, as did <hi>Job;</hi> and then
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41414:12"/>be not troubled, to ſet thy ſeal to a truth ſpoken by the father of lies, <hi>(viz.) that all that a man hath he would give for his life;</hi> Let not the dread of death tranſport thee, to accept deliverance on terms of ſinning againſt God; then be not afraid or aſhamed to let men obſerve thee ſubjected thereunto; mourn not as without hope; then ſpare not to mourn that thou muſt part from them, whoſe duty it is to mourn over thy grave.</p>
               <p>I bleſs God, I ſee in nature much; in Scripture more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant reaſon to make me willing; none to make me deſirous to dye; I look for thoſe things, and that eſtate which I will not exchange for my natural life; but I could be glad to enjoy my life and them; The cup of death is bitter; my ſtomach riſeth at, and againſt it; I cannot but pray, Oh my Father! <hi>If it be poſſible let this cup paſs from me; If it be poſſible let this cup paſs from me;</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:41414:13"/>Good Father, <hi>Let this cup paſs from me;</hi> yet, I hope I ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver want grace to ſubjoyn, <hi>not my will, but thy will be done; not my will, but thy will be done; not my will, but thy will be done:</hi> whilſt Death is Death, and I a Man, I cannot but dread it; I cannot deſire it; I will therefore endeavour to defend my ſoul a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the dread thereof; and check my paſſions, by contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting what may make me content to undergo, and cheerfully to ſtoop unto what I cannot, I dare not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire; any more then I can avoid, or dare decline it when directed by a righteous, yea, a gracious God to arreſt me; my ſoul, ſilence; ſupport thy ſelf, conſidering,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DEath is of all things moſt certain;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Death is moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain.</note> moſt ſure to overtake me; to befall me, <hi>duſt I am, and to duſt I muſt return;</hi> my life may be a while prolonged; but nothing is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41414:13"/>more certain then that death will ere long put an end unto it; <hi>man that is born of a woman, is but of few days.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My <hi>natural conſtitution is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In mans natural conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> not onely obnoxious to the aſſaults of violence from with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out; but alſo ſubject to innate corruption, principles deſtructive to it ſelf; my body is at beſt but an <hi>earthly Tabernacle,</hi> always out of repair, and ready to fall; patched up by daily bread, which will not be able to ſuſtain its being, when the <hi>grinders begin to fail;</hi> the Keepers of this my houſe do already tremble, my ſtrong men begin to bow; many diſeaſes now grow upon me; theſe are the Harbingers of mine ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching death; I do already bear in my back, the ſtone which will ere long moſt crrtainly batter in peices the earthen veſſel of my body; this Pitcher may a little while go to the Well, but it will at length come broken home.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:41414:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>The contrary elements and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, whereof my body is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded; and by which it doth now ſubſiſt, do conclude the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of my death; heat and cold, moyſture and draught, are enemies each to other; by their oppoſition my being is upheld; and yet, the <hi>militation of theſe in me,</hi> tend to the <hi>annihilation of me:</hi> The hand of violence may indeed haſten on me that eſtate, which nature will moſt certainly, moſt ſpeedily effect: the Plumb which is not plucked, will fall: the Graſs which is not cut, will wither: the ſtouteſt Oak, of longeſt growth, will at laſt come to duſt, if it be not conſumed to aſhes: my ſtrength is not the ſtrength of ſtones, nor is my fleſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raſs; I am as a dried leaf; my life paſſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way as a Weavers Shuttle, and withereth like the graſs; the Ax or Halter can onely haſten, what my ſtudy and labour is ſure to produce in a little time; if Death could not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41414:14"/>otherwiſe deſtroy my being, theſe inſtrmuments (enforced by mens cruelty) ſhould never do it, but it is an eaſie matter to break a bruiſed reed, and to force a dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life to breath out its laſt breath.</p>
               <p>My ſoul! my bodily conſtitution doth not more diſpoſe me to dye, then Gods determination doth bind me unavoidably to undergo it;
<note place="margin">By Gods determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. Heb. 9.27.</note> 
                  <hi>It is appointed unto all men,</hi> and ſo to me, <hi>once to dye:</hi> The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion God made with man in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe (when he made with him a Covenant of life) was,
<note place="margin">Gen. 2.17.</note> 
                  <hi>In the day thou eateſt of this fruit, thou ſhalt ſurely dye:</hi> the ſin was committed, the covenant was violated; this condition was judicially denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and duely executed;
<note place="margin">Rom. 5.12.</note> 
                  <hi>by one man, ſin hath paſſed on all men, and death by ſin;</hi> the ſeverity of God, hath by a moſt righteous ſentence, ſubjected all men to the ſtroke of death; am I a man, and expect to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41414:15"/>be exempted from the common fate of my nature?</p>
               <p>Immortality in the eſtate of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency,
<note place="margin">Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity not natural.</note> was of grace, not of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: created, compounded man, was capable of diſſolution;) that grace was once forfeited, never reſtored; nature therefore retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to its courſe, will inevitably work my ruine; and reſolve me into the nothing, or the duſt, out of which I was firſt made.</p>
               <p>The Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,
<note place="margin">Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed not from the ſtroak of death.</note> undoubtedly redeemed me from death; but, it is from the <hi>ſting,</hi> not from the <hi>ſtroak</hi> of death; he doth ſecure me from the <hi>curſe,</hi> the conſequences of death; but he ſtayeth not the returned <hi>courſe of nature,</hi> from paſſing on my being; hunger, cold, neakedneſs, ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſorrows, the aſſaults of vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, with all other man-deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-accidents did befal himſelf, and are incident unto me; and are as certainly as effectually deſtructive
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41414:15"/>to my being ſince, as before Chriſts death and reſurrection.</p>
               <p>I do moſt certainly believe,
<note place="margin">Some may be chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yet not I. 1 Cor. 15.51.</note> at the coming of our Lord in glory, <hi>all ſhall not dye, ſome ſhall be changed:</hi> but I have no aſſurance that I am of that number; nor is it probable; for though I live in the laſt and worſt days of the world, that laſt day is not ſo near me as my lives end; the great things which muſt be accompliſhed before that great and terrible day of the Lord come, cannot be effected in thoſe few days nature will permit me to live; nor is it probable in this preſent age; I will not envy the Saints then li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, the happineſs of never dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but my ſoul; I ſee no reaſon of hope, that I ſhould partake thereof.</p>
               <p>Nature diſpoſing me unto death; God having determined death to paſs upon me; I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not avoid it; it will with certainty overtake me at the laſt: It may o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertake
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41414:16"/>me ſooner then I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware or look for it; I have not the certainty of one days exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from this moſt certain condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; I am ſubject to many caſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as well as diſeaſes; a tile from an houſe, or a fall from my horſe, might ſoon kill me if I were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad; Death commeth on me where ever I am, as an armed man whom I cannot reſiſt; and come to me the worſt that can come, it is but death, which I can no way ſhun, or long avoid.</p>
               <p>My Soul! be wiſe; make a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of neceſſity; ſtoop quietly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that ſtroke from which thou canſt not ſtir: Startle not in ſence of that ſtate, from which there is no ſtarting: Whether I conſume my ſelf, or be cut down by others, it is but death; this eſtate doth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidably attend me: Let me be content chearfully, ſubmiſſively to bear the evil I am no more able to divert, then to deſire; ſhall I
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41414:16"/>ſtomack to entertain the gueſt, whom I daily expect, and who commeth with command, and ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſiſtable power; whoſe coming I cannot prevent or delay; who being come, will not be diſmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed or ſent back for one moment: I will bid welcome the certain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable event, though haſtned by an uncertain, unexpected ſtroak.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. II.</head>
               <p>DEath is not more certain to me,
<note place="margin">Death is a common ſtate.</note> then <hi>common to men:</hi> this is the lot of all men; the man liveth not who ſhall not feel the ſtroak of Death; ſtrong or weak, rich or poor, noble or ignoble, good or bad, muſt all die:
<note place="margin">Great men die.</note> The power of Princes may precipitate and haſten the death of others, but it cannot protect themſelves from the ſtroak of death, no not for a moment; as for thoſe who have riches,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 49.7, 8.</note> there is not one of them can <hi>redeem his brothers,</hi> no, nor yet his own <hi>life
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41414:17"/>from death;</hi> when I die I ſhall reſt with <hi>Kings and Counſellors of the earth;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 3.13, 14.</note> 
                  <hi>with Princes who had gold, who filled their houſes with ſilver:</hi> Death hath ſubdued the moſt dreadful Conquerors of the world, and devoured the moſt puiſſant Armies:
<note place="margin">Strong men die.</note> Where are now the Sons of <hi>Anack?</hi> what is become of the Giants of whom we read? are they not dead? could <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> ſtrength repel, or <hi>Davids</hi> Worthies ſtand under and againſt the ſtroke of death?
<note place="margin">Beſt men dye.</note> Piety is no priviledge againſt the arreſt of death;
<note place="margin">John 8.52, 53.</note> are not the Patriarcks faln aſleep? where are the Fathers of old? do the Prophets live for ever? the beſt that ever lived, died: death is an high way, a beaten road, this tract is trodden; <hi>Abel, Adam, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch, Noah, Abraham, David, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel, Peter, Paul, James, John,</hi> yea the Lord Chriſt himſelf are all dead; theſe with multitudes of all ſorts, ranks, qualities, langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41414:17"/>and degrees, have gone this way before me; why then do I fear to follow after them?</p>
               <p>Death is not more common in its general nature,
<note place="margin">The kind of death is alſo common.</note> then in its <hi>ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al kind:</hi> Violent death by all ways of ignominy, and inſtruments of cruelty are common to men; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to Martyrs, and Gods moſt faithful Miniſters: this way Gods Prophets, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rijah, Iſaiah, Zechariah,</hi> and others: Chriſts Diſciples, <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Paul, James, John</hi> and others: The Primitive Fathers of the Church, <hi>Polycarpus, Ignatius, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinius</hi> and others: And our firſt Reformers from Popiſh blindneſs, and abominations, <hi>Cranmer, Ridley, Latimer, Hooper, Rogers, Bradford, Taylor, Saunders,</hi> and many others went out of the world: What day returneth without the death of men? what age of the world hath paſſed not ſtained with the blood of Martyrs, or violent death of holy men? what kind of death pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41414:18"/>to malefactors, hath not Gods Miniſters and Martyrs, the zealous reprovers of publick ſin, been ſubjected to, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone?</p>
               <p>My Soul! be thy condition what it can, thou muſt conclude, there doth no temptation befall me but what is common to man,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.13.</note> yea to the beſt of men, and to the cheif of Martyrs: what if the way be dirty and dreadful, tedious and tireſome; ſhall I draw back? or not drive after ſo many, ſo good, ſuch excellent men as are gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me, <hi>Levius communia tangunt,</hi> ſay men by nature; how eaſie is a common yoke? whilſt then mine is the common ſtate of men, and good men; abate thy fears, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance thy courage; follow with chearfulneſs and content: Let the motto of the happy, unhappy Lady <hi>Jane Gray</hi> give check to the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring cenſures of the ſpectators of my death;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:41414:18"/>
                  <q>Non aliena putes, homini qua obtingere poſſunt;</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sors hodierna mihi, tunc erit illa ſibi.</hi> I tread no untroden tract; I am not the firſt, I ſhall not be the laſt that dye; I go the way that many, moſt, and beſt have gone before me; and others muſt daily and hourly follow after me: what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is my chance, death is the condition common to men; and the grave doth know no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them who run out the courſe of nature, and thoſe who are cut off by violence; <hi>One dieth in his full ſtrength,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 21.23, 24, 25, 26.</note> 
                  <hi>being wholly at eaſe, and quiet, his breaſts are ful of milk, and his bones are moiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with marrow; another dieth in the bitterneſs of his ſoul, and never eateth with pleaſure; theſe both lye down alike in the duſt, and the worm ſhall cover them,</hi> without any dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference or diſtinction; Let me dye which way God hath deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, by ſickneſs, or by ſword,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41414:19"/>in my bed, or on a publique ſtage, in old age, or in the prime of my days; in courſe of nature, or by the hands of violence, I can but dye; and dye I muſt, for I am a man; and death is common, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and natural unto man.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. III.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DEath</hi> this common ſtate,
<note place="margin">My death is decreed by God.</note> with all its circumſtances is <hi>determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Lord:</hi> whatſoever doth relate unto this condition, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in the councels of the moſt high; theſe no man can alter, or avoid; God is of ſoveraign power; his purpoſes muſt and ſhall prevail againſt all powers whatſoever; what is by him decreed muſt ſtand moſt certainly to come to paſs.</p>
               <p>My time is then in the hands of the Lord, he will preſerve me from the force of any diſeaſe, and fury of the oppreſſor, until the date by him determined be expired; <hi>my time is appointed on the earth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 14.5.</note> 
                  <hi>my days are determined, the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41414:19"/>of my moneths are with the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty; he hath ſet the bounds there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of;</hi> Theſe I cannot, I muſt not expect to paſs; nor can the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers of nature, moſt violent diſeaſes; or the fury, malice, or power of men, break in upon them, to anticipate their courſe, or accelerate their period; I cannot, I ſhall not be cut down before the time; nor any other way then that God hath decreed; ſhall not I be willing to go, <hi>when</hi> and <hi>how</hi> God will have me go?</p>
               <p>The decrees of Heaven are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alterable, and unavoidable; it is mans duty to ſubmit to them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out demur or debate; Shall I, can I profeſs a filial relation to God, and obedience to the will of him my Father, and not reſign up my ſelf, my time, and my life to be diſpoſed by God? is a relu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctancy in this caſe competible with my prayer, <hi>thy will be done?</hi> or conſiſtent with that my reſolved
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41414:20"/>ſupplication in this very caſe, <hi>not my will but thy will be done?</hi> men are but like diſeaſes, executioners of Gods decree upon me; they have againſt me no power but what is given them from above; though therefore I am loath to leave my cottage, and preſent ſenſible com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, ſhall I dare to reſiſt? or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe chearfully to yeild unto, and reſign them at the pleaſure of mine abſolute Lord and Soveraign, by which alone, I hold them?</p>
               <p>Conſider, Oh my ſoul! it is the Lord (more righteous then to do me wrong, more gracious then to do me hurt) who doth diſpoſe my time and ſtate; Let him do what ſeemeth good unto him: <hi>There is a ſeaſon to every thing under the Sun;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 3.1, 11.</note> there is <hi>a time to every purpoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the Heaven:</hi> Gods time is the ſet time to all things; and the beſt time to the Sons of men: <hi>every thing is beautiful in its time;</hi> ſo ſhall death be to me, when my time
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41414:20"/>is come; when mens work is done it is fit they go to bed, lye down and ſleep; <hi>man goeth forth to his work, and to his labour,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. 104.23.</note> 
                  <hi>until the evening:</hi> When Corn is ripe it muſt be cut done; I ſhall not fall with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Gods determinate counſel; ſhall I dare? can I deſire to contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict that? I ſhall not be cut down until I be ripe; and my cutting down be ſeaſonable; can I wiſh to ſtand longer? I have lived, ſhall I not now be content to dye, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Gods determination?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IV.</head>
               <p>THe aſſaults of Death, are the aſſaults of an <hi>enemy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Death is an enemy, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered.</note> 
                  <hi>armed with power and irreſiſtible.</hi> This is very true! but yet, Death is the <hi>laſt enemy</hi> I muſt encounter; and cannot be otherwiſe conquered then by my falling under its ſtroak: my whole life hath been a militati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and my death is but a mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary finiſhing of my courſe: my willingneſs to dye; mine encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41414:21"/>this King of terrors with a Chriſtian faith; with a calm, quiet, and compoſed Spirit; can onely make my dying words trumpet with triumph,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.7.</note> 
                  <hi>I have fought a good fight, I have finiſhed my courſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have all my life-time fought with Death, as <hi>Sampſon</hi> with the <hi>Philiſtines;</hi> it often aſſaulteth me by hunger, nakedneſs, cold, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-weakneſs, ſickneſs, natural diſeaſes, and the aſſaults of vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence: ſhall I think it ſtrange to receive another onſet, and to take one turn more with my conſtant enemy? Shall I fear by the <hi>power of grace,</hi> to vanquiſh him, whom I have by the <hi>ſtrength of nature,</hi> and <hi>help of art,</hi> I many times reſiſted and repelled.</p>
               <p>O my ſoul! Sin my <hi>Dalilah,</hi> hath deceived me; and ſpoiled me of my natural ſtrength; I cannot now, as formerly, fight with, and beat back this <hi>Philiſtine:</hi> mine onely conqueſt of him, is to fall before,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41414:21"/>and with him: when he hath di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided my body from my ſoul, he hath done his worſt; and will ſoon find a few ſuch victories will waſte his ſtrength, ſo that he ſhall not be able to keep the field; to appear in the world; or to aſſault the ſons of men.</p>
               <p>My ſoul! conſider thy preſent ſtate; compoſe thy ſelf; cry unto God for ſtrength of faith; that thou mayſt by dying, be at once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged on thine enemy: I ſhall when dead, be for ever freed from that warfare, with Satan, Sin, and the World, which I have been conſtrained to wage all my life long: I ſhall then no longer fight for my <hi>ſtrength, youth, growth, credit, comforts,</hi> and <hi>conſcience,</hi> all which I have all my time defended with much difficulty, and great danger: Death mine enemy, ſhall then ſet me free from the <hi>Devils temptation, the worlds enticements, the outrage of men, the arrows of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41414:22"/>the Almighty, and the luſtings of mine own fleſh;</hi> all which have all my days ſtung my ſoul, and bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered my body. My ſoul! take courage unto this laſt encounter; herein my willingneſs to dye, is the victory; my fall is the fulleſt conqueſt that I ever did, or can make: be herein the more couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, conſidering,</p>
               <p>Death is, though an enemy, yet a <hi>conquered, and diſarmed enemy:</hi> Chriſt, that Captain of my ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, hath tryed the ſtrength of death, and ſubdued it; he by dying did overcome death, and him who had the power of death, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the Devil: herein Satan was out ſhot in his own Bow, and caught in his own ſnare: what gained the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> by bringing forth <hi>Sampſon</hi> to make them ſport; and to be inſulted over, in the houſe of <hi>Dagon;</hi> but their own deſtruction? the very ſame hath death and the Devil gotten by
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:41414:22"/>bringing the Lord of life to dye on the Croſs; and to the Grave which could not hold him; theſe by getting, have loſt the victory: O bleſſed Paradox! by this my faith, and my ſoul can out-face, out-brave death; whilſt my nature, and my body doth dread the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults, and ſtroak thereof. Death ſtruck the Lord of life with its ſting; and loſt its ſting by ſtriking him: and in him, all that are his, do ever ſince inſult over death; with an, <hi>O death!</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.55.</note> 
                  <hi>where is thy ſting? O grave! where is thy victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry?</hi> Since this foil death is befooled of its conqueſt over them whom it moſt inſultingly ſtrikes with ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, and cutteth down with power; for it prevailing, looſeth its deſign: The deſign of Death is to <hi>ſeal man under indelible guilt;</hi> to <hi>ſet him under the curſe of the Law; and at everlaſting diſtance from the Lord:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">verſ. 56.58</note> 
                  <hi>The ſting of Death is Sin; the ſtrength of Sin is the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41414:23"/>Law; but thanks be unto God, who hath given us the victory, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord;</hi> for hereby death doth (to all that are in Chriſt Jeſus) effect what is directly contrary to its deſign, it <hi>diſcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that guilt</hi> under which they greived all their days; and <hi>releaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them from thoſe curſes of the Law,</hi> by which they were chaſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this life; and it <hi>tranſmitteth their ſouls unto the immediate and eternal enjoyment of God and Chriſt;</hi> and although it holdeth the body for ſome time, yet, it <hi>divideth it not from Chriſt,</hi> to whom it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeperably united; and by whom it ſhall be raiſed up, to be reuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the ſoul, and perfectly poſſeſs God for ever.</p>
               <p>My Soul! why art thou afraid of a Bee which hath loſt its ſting? why doſt thou dread an enemy van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed to thy hand, and ſprawl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at thy feet? Hath <hi>David</hi> kill'd <hi>Goliah,</hi> and ſhall not trembling,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:41414:23"/>affrighted <hi>Iſrael</hi> up, and purſue the <hi>Philiſtines?</hi> hath the Lord Chriſt gotten and given me the victory over death, by diſcharging thy guilt, and bearing the puniſhment thereof in his own body, unto the ſatisfaction of the Law; and wilt thou fear to encounter the fierceſt aſſaults thereof? What? ſhall a conquered enemy diſani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate the Conqueror?</p>
               <p>My Soul! in the world <hi>thou haſt tribulation;</hi> in death <hi>thou haſt ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror;</hi> but be of good comfort thou art now engaged in the laſt encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with both; and the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus hath <hi>overcome the world,</hi> and <hi>conquered death:</hi> Triumph in death; for thou ſhalt by dying, be made triumphant over Death, the World and the Devil: Thy warfare is now accompliſhed; let me now in my laſt act play the man, and ſhew the valour of my Faith and Patience, unto the due reſtraint of my now provoked fear and paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſions:
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:41414:24"/>Then this ſhall be the matter of mine eternal happineſs and honour, that <hi>I have warred a good warfare; I have fought a good fight, I have kept the Faith.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. V.</head>
               <p>DEath is a <hi>curſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed nature of death is chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</note> the <hi>puniſhment of mans ſin,</hi> the <hi>expreſſion of Gods wrath,</hi> and the <hi>execution of the Law;</hi> and <hi>dreadful ſentence</hi> pronounced againſt man. It is ſo, in its nature, and of it ſelf: But it is not ſuch to all that are thereto ſubjected: the voyce from heaven hath proclaimed them <hi>Bleſſed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 14.13.</note> 
                  <hi>who dye in the Lord,</hi> and hath rendred two reaſons of the bleſſed ſtate of their death: Firſt, they <hi>reſt from their labour;</hi> they then reap no pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment,
<note place="margin">Heb. 4.10</note> but are indeed bleſſed; for <hi>he that is entred into his reſt, ceaſeth from his own works</hi> (of ſin and ſorrow) <hi>as God ceaſed from his.</hi> Secondly, <hi>Their works follow them,</hi> unto their acceptance with, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence from the Lord.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:41414:24"/>
               <p>The nature of death is changed to ſuch who are in Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Death to Chriſts friends is a ſleep.</note> and to ſuch who die for Chriſt; the friends of Chriſt do not dye, but <hi>ſleep:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 7.21.</note> I account ſleep a ſpecial bleſſing of God, for the refreſhment of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: my ſleep is the image the ſimilitude of death: Death is the trueſt, the onely ſleep of a true Beleiver; when I ſleep I am as dead; and when I dye I ſhall but ſleep: I ſhall indeed ſleep longer in my grave, then in my bed; but I am ſure I ſhall ſleep more quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; without affrighting fancies, or diſturbing dreams, and I ſhall at length awake and ariſe: when my weary day is ended, how will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing am I to lye down and ſleep? My Soul! art thou not willing thy wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry body ſhould have reſt? to dye is to a Saint no more, then to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs and go to bed, to lie down and ſleep;
<note place="margin">Joh. 11.11</note> Let what will become of <hi>Dives, our friend Lazarus ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:41414:25"/>
               <p>The righteous when they dye, are <hi>taken from evil to come:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 57.1, 2 and 26.20</note> death is their defence from danger, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs and dread; their grave is Gods <hi>pavilion</hi> and <hi>receptacle,</hi> into which they his <hi>jewels</hi> are gathered,
<note place="margin">Mal. 3.17.</note> leſt they ſhould be left in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions of the world; in which, they his truſty friends and confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates are ſecured from the ſtorm and blaſt of the terrible ones, rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up by the Lord to ſhake terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly the earth: my Soul! what though the Chambers of death be dark; wilt thou deem it a curſe to be gathered into them by Gods ſpecial grace; that thou mayſt not feel, hear or ſee the evil, which his wrath and vengeance is about to bring on the places of thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent abode? The juſt by death <hi>enter into peace,</hi> when the whole world is full of Wars; they <hi>reſt in their beds</hi> when the houſe is all in an hurly burly, and unquiet tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult: Death is the Saints ceſſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:41414:25"/>from labour and travel; their ſecurity from lamentation and trouble: their eſtate of quiet and eaſe, and their entrance into reſt and glory: The very wicked (who with <hi>Balaam,</hi> are ready to curſe them whilſt they live) would gladly ſhare lots with them in their death: The worſt of men are ſo apprehenſive and affected that their latter end ſhall be exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly good, that they cannot but wiſh to dye the death of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous.</p>
               <p>Death is indeed a curſe to ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; but the <hi>courſe of nature unto Saints:</hi> The direful exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioner of Gods wrath and law, to all who die in their ſin; but a <hi>meſſenger of divine favour</hi> to all who die in the Lord; <hi>an harbinger of peace</hi> to all who walk in upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: A grim Porter to <hi>fetch home to their fathers manſions,</hi> all that are Gods children. Death is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a diſmal doom on the ſons of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:41414:26"/>the firſt <hi>Adam,;</hi> but the <hi>diſcharge of all ſin, ſorrow, pain,</hi> and <hi>travel</hi> to all the ſons of the ſecond <hi>Adam:</hi> death is in its nature vile and odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 116.15.</note> but <hi>precious in the ſight of the Lord, is the death of all his Saints:</hi> death is exceeding dreadful to ſuch who are obnoxious to its <hi>ſting;</hi> but the ſtroak of death is deſireable, to all ſuch who are acquitted from, and armed againſt its <hi>ſting.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Death by violence containeth in it a curſe,
<note place="margin">A good cauſe, and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, make death a bleſſing.</note> with an emphaſis; and increaſe: yet, <hi>a good conſcience, righteouſneſs towards God; and the teſtimony of Jeſus;</hi> being the cauſe procuring the ſame; maketh the moſt baſe, ignominious, and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed death, a condition of glory and bleſſedneſs: the bleſſing of them who dye in the Lord; doth moſt certainly, eminently, and eſpecially appertain to ſuch who dye for the Lord.
<note place="margin">Phil. 1.29.</note> It is a ſingular gift to <hi>beleive in Chriſt;</hi> but <hi>to ſuffer,</hi> and that unto death, for
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:41414:26"/>Chriſt, is a peculiar gift, of ſpecial grace; all Saints ſhare not in it; attain not the honour of it: <hi>Stephen</hi> ſtoned for enforcing the truth of Religion (by the ſtrength of reaſon,
<note place="margin">Act. 7, 55, 56.</note> not to be reſiſted by the adverſaries,) ſaw, <hi>Heaven open to receive him at his death:</hi> The ſlain for the Word of God, and teſtimony which they held, are <hi>lodged under Gods Altar in glory;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 6.9.10, 11.</note> and before the <hi>Throne of the Lamb;</hi> they are cloathed in <hi>white robes,</hi> to attend the Lamb: the moſt curſed and ignominious death is changed and made glorious to juſt men, by having paſſed on Gods beſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; moſt zealous and faithful Prophets; yea, the only and beloved Son of God, the Lord Jeſus, our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, hath made death, every, any kind of death the bleſſing of his people.</p>
               <p>My Soul! miſtake not the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of death, unto the increaſe of thy dread: mind the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; make ſure of the qualification
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:41414:27"/>which changeth its nature; and then death will looſe its affrighting vizard, and have another aſpect in thine eye; and thou wilt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline to give it a more free ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance: am I in Chriſt? I am then redeemed from the curſe of death; can I? dare I deſire to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the courſe of nature? Beware, O my ſoul! who am I? <hi>Shall the earth be removed for me?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 18 4.</note> ſhall I think to alter Gods purpoſe? or to change the courſe of Gods provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence towards men? ſhall I not be ſatisfied to be ſaved from the ſting, unleſs I eſcape alſo the ſtroak of Death? God never pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, Chriſt never promiſed to free me from this; why do I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to dream of it, to look for it? Shall my dread of the ſtroak, darken the glory of Chriſts love, or damp mine apprehenſions, and eſteem of the unſpeakable, unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved mercy of being ſaved from the ſting of death? God forbid.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:41414:27"/>God hath extracted the poyſon; ſhall my ſtomach nauſeate and riſe againſt this cup, onely becauſe it is bitter? Oh no; I will right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfully take it, as the cup of ſalvation; and diſmiſs my dread; and dutifully ſubmit my ſelf to the Will of God, onely wiſe; my moſt gracious Father: O my God, <hi>not my will but thy Will be done.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God hath accounted poor, weak, worthleſs me, worthy of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of the glorious Goſpel of his dear Son, he hath at this time culled me from among my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, to bear a ſpecial Teſtimony to his truth; to the power, plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, purity, and ſimplicity of Chriſts ordinances, worſhip and officers; and to thoſe degrees of reformation in this Church and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which have been proteſted and ſolemnly ſworn to the moſt high God; herein I have beleived; for theſe I have ſpoken, written, and diſputed; and ſhall I now
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:41414:28"/>fear to ſuffer? ſhall I now dread death, the crowning act of all my zeal, diligence and fidelity? is not this part of the croſs of Chriſt? and ſo, the glorious crown of a Miniſter of the Goſpel? have I any thing wherein to glory, ſave the Croſs of Chriſt? and ſhall I fear to be ſeen in my Maſters Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very? the honour of my now ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected death, is an high favour, a peculiar priviledge, an effect of ſpecial grace; and therefore ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to perſwade me to be, not onely willing, but deſirous to be offered up by death; to, and for him who accounted not his life dear for me: Death in, and for this cauſe, is not more my duty then my dignity; the more igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minious it is, the more glorious; it ſhall receive the due recompence of reward;
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.12.</note> 
                  <hi>If I ſuffer with Chriſt, I ſhall be glorified with him;</hi> and <hi>raign with him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have all my days wandred in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:41414:28"/>this world like a Pilgrim in a ſtrange Country; it is now my Fathers pleaſure to call and ſend for me home; ſhall I refuſe to go in the hand of a grim Meſſenger? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his gaſtly look, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighting countenance? may not the ſame bloody hand conduct me to my Fathers Houſe, which doth cut down mine and my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers foes? what though the ſtroak of death be the ſame to good and bad? the ſequels of Death are not the ſame to both: the Red Sea may paſs <hi>Iſrael</hi> into the land of reſt, and yet ruine the <hi>Egyptians:</hi> the ſame Sheriff who doth execute Traytours and malefactours, doth put good ſubjects into the poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their proprieties; though he be dreadful in the one, his very <hi>poſſe comitatus</hi> is deſireable to the other: Shall I fooliſhly draw back, fear to be poſſeſſed of mine <hi>inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance incorruptible, and undefiled,</hi> becauſe I muſt be brought, and put
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:41414:29"/>into it with Halberts, Bills, Swords, and the Sheriffs train and power?</p>
               <p>My Soul; chear up; reflect on thy ſelf; Chriſt his love; and Gods grace; notwithſtanding my many ſlips, falls, and infirmities; I will preſume to ſay, I have lived the life of the righteous; the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of God is on my fleſh; with God I have deſired and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to walk; though I have ſometimes wandred, and gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray like a loſt ſheep: I have embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Chriſt my Lord; and to him I will cleave, as to my deer Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer; I ſhall therefore dye the death of the righteous: although I may be ſtruck, I ſhall not be ſtung by death: Death may paſs upon me as the courſe of nature, and as an expreſſion of humane rage, but not as the curſe of God; or execution of his Law: Let me make it my care to ſee my quality changed whilſt I live; and then I am aſſured God will change the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:41414:29"/>quality of my death when I dye.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VI.</head>
               <p>IF I now dye, as mens rage doth threaten; mine enemies deſire and hope; my friends fear and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precate; and my ſelf have cauſe to expect; <hi>I dye as a Malefactour;</hi> and by the ſentence of a righteous Law, well, and what then?
<note place="margin">Such is the Stat. of <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. the only law declaring Treaſon.</note> if I do thus dye, my guilt is <hi>real</hi> or <hi>reputed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Suppoſe my guilt were <hi>real</hi> (for Lord thou knoweſt mine innocency wherein I ſtand defamed) to die a malefactor is not inconſiſtent with eternal ſalvation: I may die for my ſin, and not dye in my ſin: I may be moſt juſtly puniſhed by men (that others may <hi>hear, and fear,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 13.11.</note> 
                  <hi>and do no more ſo wickedly</hi>) for that ſin which may be pardoned by the Lord: I may be condemned in the world for that crime, which ſhall never be charged on me by my God: my preſent puniſhment may provoke my repentance; and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:41414:30"/>my repentance will moſt certainly procure me Gods, if not the Kings mercy: Divine grace is not barred by humane juſtice: the theif cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified with Chriſt, received (and confeſſed ſo much) the <hi>due reward of his evil;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 23.41, 43.</note> yet this hindred not his <hi>ſouls being that night in Paradiſe with his Saviour</hi> and fellow-ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer: The crime, not the condition, muſt divide between God and the ſoul; as it doth divide the ſoul from the body: but repentance is the ſpunge of guilt; where God giveth repentance, he denieth not remiſſion of the moſt egregious crime; to the moſt heinous offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor: The hand of humane juſtice may be the help of the ſinners re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; and then <hi>Tyburn,</hi> or <hi>Tower-hill</hi> may be as near, as good, yea, a much better way to Heaven then any other: Happy is the ſtroke of juſtice,
<note place="margin">2 Chron. 33.12.</note> which may ſave the ſoul from hell. <hi>Manaſſeh's</hi> fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters made him ſee, confeſs, and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:41414:30"/>abandon his ſin: the Elect of God are not exempt from the greateſt crimes; they may fall into and commit them: But this is their happineſs, they are ſure to repent thereof; and therefore they ſhall not be eternally condemned for them. I envy not ſome late con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, executed malefactors,
<note place="margin">The mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therous Judges of his late Majeſty K.<hi>C.</hi> firſt.</note> their confidence of ſalvation, and eternal life; but I heartily wiſh that (for the glory of God, the honour of Chriſtian martyrdom, credit of true Religion, the real comfort of their friends; as well as their own ſalvation) they had more freely and more openly owned their guilt (moſt odious in the light of nature, much more of Scripture) confeſſed their ſin; and juſtified God and man by their contrition, and due confuſion un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the juſt ſentence of a moſt righteous law: I cannot but think repentance had been more proper matter for their profeſſions, then
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:41414:31"/>their inſultation and rejoycing in their ſufferings, as if in and for the Lord; and their peace, joy and courage, whereof their ſurviving friends boaſt; not obſerving the ſame abſtracted from that humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, and penſive demeanour, moſt Chriſtianly ſuitable to ſo juſt, and ſad ſufferings.</p>
               <p>If there be in me any real guilt, for which I have deſerved to dye; I pray God convince me of it (for I yet ſee it not) and affect me with it: if in any thing I have violated the Law, though through error, or ignorance, God give me grace to juſtifie the righteouſneſs of that law by which I may be condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and then if my ſuffering the ſentence of the law work in me a ſence of guilt, unto a penitential ſubmiſſion under the hand of God, through faith in Chriſt my Saviour, I ſhall ſee cauſe to confeſs Gods abundant goodneſs, in ſaving my ſoul, by the condemnation,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:41414:31"/>execution, and loſs of my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by.</p>
               <p>But O Lord, thou knoweſt the crime by which I ſtand defamed; &amp; for which, I may be unjuſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, is <hi>reputed</hi> and not <hi>real;</hi> for my heart never yet admitted, or entertained the leaſt evil thought againſt the King, <hi>the Lords anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted:</hi> if then I dye in mine inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, and as a malefactor; my death may adminiſter to me more joy then greif, more comfort then contrition, more confidence then confuſion; for howſoever men may condemn me, God, and mine own conſcience will acquit and juſtifie me: Nor am I the firſt, the only one, that hath been oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in judgement; this is one of the common evils under the ſun, belonging to Gods immediate &amp; pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar vengeance:
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.15. and 5.8.</note> there is <hi>a juſt man that periſheth in his righteouſneſs; if thou ſeeſt the oppreſſion of the poor, and the violent perverting of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:41414:32"/>and judgement in a Provinces marvail not at the matter; for he that is higher then the higheſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeth it, and he is higher then they.</hi> I pray God prevent <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> King and Kingdom from ſlay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing poor,
<note place="margin">In this God hath graciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red my deſire.</note> envied, and deſpiſed me; for mine innocent blood will hurt them, more then their ſtroak can poſſibly hurt me; they can but kill my body; work for me the glory of a martyr; ſend me to my place and ſtate of reſt: but this will hazard their ſouls, gall their conſciences, caſt them under the guilt, and odium of violence, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution and murther by the ſword of juſtice; ſtain the land with blood which will cry for Gods vengeance and their repentance; <hi>As for me, I am in your hands, do with me as ſeemeth good and meet unto you; But know ye for certain, that if ye put me to death, ye ſhall ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bring innocent blood upon your ſelves, upon this City, and upon the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:41414:32"/>inhabitants thereof; for of a truth the Lord hath ſent me, and ſtirred me up to ſpeak and write all the words which I have ſounded in your ears.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The reproach of my ſuffering as a malefactor, will indeed, and for a time cloud my credit; dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken my ſufferings, and deprive God of the honour of them, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them a ſtone of ſtumbling to many; a rock of offence to the weak and wicked: but they ſhall not in the leaſt eclipſe the glory of my ſufferings, and innocency, in the ſight of God and good men; or in the ſence of mine own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: As for me; let all men know, I wait for a reſurrection of <hi>names,</hi> as well, as certainly, as a reſurrection of <hi>bodies,</hi> when the great Judge of all the Gods on earth, ſhall appear to call over the proceſs, take cognizance of the error, and reverſe the falſe judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment paſſed by the ſons of the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:41414:33"/>mighty. Whilſt my God, and my conſcience witneſs, true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, enforced by right reaſon, to be whole, the onely, and the real cauſe of my ſuffering; why ſhould I be troubled at the clamour, and ſeeming black charge of <hi>Treaſon,</hi> whilſt the fulfilling my miniſtry, and the faithful diſchardge of my duty, is the real ground, and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cauſe of mens wrath, and my death; Shall I be diſmayed, that I am Arraigned, Condemned, and executed ſo, as to be reputed a Malefactor? have not all Gods Prophets and Apoſtles been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the World as <hi>evil do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers?</hi> and as ſuch, expoſed unto, and derided in their ſufferings? was not <hi>Jeremiah</hi> charged with <hi>Treaſon?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 37.13, 15. Act. 24.5</note> and <hi>Paul</hi> with <hi>Sedition?</hi> and both as ſuch impriſoned and afflicted: <hi>Elijah</hi> was the <hi>troubler of</hi> Iſrael; was not <hi>Amos</hi> expelled the Court as a <hi>Dangerous Preacher againſt the King;</hi> was not <hi>Michaiah</hi> carged
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:41414:33"/>by the King, to be one that <hi>bare ill will to the King?</hi> was not this the very lot of <hi>Chriſt himſelf?</hi> ſuffered not that righteous one, as a <hi>Blaſphemer,</hi> and as an <hi>enemy to Caeſar?</hi> ſhall I be deterred from following my Maſter? from drinking of the cup, whereof my deer redeemer hath begun? from travelling in the beaten road of all Gods Prophets? the very way pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by the Lord himſelf? hath not the Lord Chriſt declared hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane rage and reproach, to attend all who faithfully reveal his will, and mens ſins? is not unjuſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach in my death, part of Chriſts croſs, and my Crown? why then do I dread and decline it? if I be reproached for the name of Chriſt, I am happy,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.14</note> 
                  <hi>the ſpirit of glory, and of Chriſt reſteth on me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is the <hi>cauſe,</hi> not the <hi>pain,</hi> maketh the <hi>Martyr,</hi> or <hi>Malefactor,</hi> my ſoul, be not troubled at the kind, or clamoured cauſe of my death: were I indeed really guilty;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:41414:34"/>did I receive the due reward of my ſin, I muſt then have laid my mouth in the duſt, confeſſed my ſin; given glory to God, accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the puniſhment of mine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, and by an humble act of faith applied the blood of Chriſt to my ſoul; then I might reſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured that I was <hi>condemned in and by the world,</hi> that <hi>I might not be judged of the Lord.</hi> But whilſt if I dye, as I now dread, I dye in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocently, for a good conſcience, and for the Teſtimony of the truth; Let me rejoyce that God hath ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted me worthy to be reputed the <hi>off-ſcowring of this world,</hi> and <hi>enemy of mankind;</hi> for my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is of the Lord, who judgeth moſt righteous judgement; and though <hi>my brethren caſt me out,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 66.5.</note> 
                  <hi>and cry; Let the Lord be glorified; yet, he will appear to my joy, and they ſhall be aſhamed;</hi> when Jeſus Chriſt ſhall come to judge, clear, and crown me as his Martyr; it ſhall
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:41414:34"/>not repent me that men condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and cut me off as a <hi>Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VII.</head>
               <p>IN death I ſhall <hi>feel pain;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Death is painful, but puts an end to pain.</note> It is like I may; yet, God can make it eaſie: I feel more pain in the <hi>precurſors,</hi> then I can feel in the <hi>ſtroak of death:</hi> the pain and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of a killing diſeaſe, is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and ordinarily more, then the pain of death; it is uſually ſuch as maketh life a burden, and death defireable; how many in the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of a Feavor, a fit of the Stone, or Collique, have wiſhed for death to eaſe them of their pain? my fear of pain in death is much greater, then what I ſhall feel in the ſtroak thereof; the pomp and paſſage unto death, doth, and will more perplex my ſoul, then the pain thereof can poſſibly pinch my ſence: but ſuppoſe the worſt; yet,</p>
               <p>The greateſt pains of death are
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:41414:35"/>
                  <hi>tolerable,</hi> and <hi>paſs away in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> with how much eaſe did the Lord Jeſus <hi>give up the Ghoſt,</hi> in that dying act, the dreadful ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of which, made him ſweat blood and water? how many of the Martyrs have with moſt calm and compoſed ſpirits, lien under the moſt cruel and exquiſite tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and as Lambs before the Shearer, breathed out their laſt breath in the greateſt pains of death, that envy could deviſe, or enraged malice could inflict? <hi>Haukes</hi> (that holy Martyr, in our <hi>Marian</hi> Perſecution) in the midſt of the flames, did not forget to lift up his hands towards Heaven, before he gave up the Ghoſt; as a token to his Friends, that the <hi>raging pain of that ſiery death was tolerable.</hi> All Gods Saints have lien on this rack; and ſitten down on this little eaſe; and ſhall I give back becauſe of a little tolerable pain? Be the pains of death never
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:41414:35"/>ſo peircing ſharp, and intolerable; yet they are <hi>ſhort,</hi> ſoon paſs away; and are the <hi>Period of all pain;</hi> in reſpect of this, nature hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and Scripture hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly concluded,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.2.</note> 
                  <hi>better is the day of a mans death, then the day of his birth:</hi> all my life hath been nothing elſe but <hi>ſorrow and pain;</hi> my days have hitherto paſſed in anguiſh, affliction, and anxiety; yea, my reſting time, place, and ſtate, hath <hi>ſcared me with Dreams,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.13, 14.</note> 
                  <hi>and terrified me with Viſions in the night, ſo that ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling death, any kind of death, hath been more deſireable then life;</hi> Shall I now fear that one ſtroak, which though it cut me to the heart, will at once cut off all my pain and greif? doth not na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture teach men to chuſe the pain of cutting off an Arm or Leg, rather then to lye conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually under a feſtring, burning, and incurable wound? <hi>Plotinus</hi>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:41414:36"/>the Philoſopher, accounted mens mortallity, Gods ſpecial mercy, as the expiration of their miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: <hi>Cato Major,</hi> that wiſe <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> reflecting the pains he had endured, profeſſed if he might be rendred young again, and renew his age, he would not deſire it; he would refuſe it: Did the pain of life, take away the pain of death to Heathens? and ſhall it not much more do ſo unto Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, who have other, and better hopes of future happineſs then they ever knew or expected?</p>
               <p>My ſoul! ſtir up thy ſelf, make out a little faith and patience to endure this one pinch, and ſtroak of pain, which ſhall preſently ceaſe and be the period of all thy miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; the cure of all thy maladies; and will heal thee of all thy fears, griefs, cares, diſeaſes, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers: the afflictions of my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and anguiſh of my mind: though I walk through the <hi>vale of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:41414:36"/>the ſhadow of death I will fear none ill; for Lord thou art with me:</hi> be with me O my God, that I may not over-paſſionately fear that little ſhort pain I muſt feel; make thou a <hi>lively faith</hi> in me, to bear up under, prevail againſt, and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph over a <hi>lively ſence;</hi> that ſo my laſt little pain being paſt, I may poſſeſs eternal health and eaſe; and therein rejoyce, for that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the ſtroak of death did for preſent cut, it did for ever cure my ſoul.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VIII.</head>
               <p>DEath will deprive me of all <hi>ſenſible pleaſure:</hi> it will ſo;
<note place="margin">Death de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priveth of pleaſures, but they are ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</note> and it is no matter; for this plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure was at beſt but <hi>ſenſible;</hi> my ſoul found no pleaſure in it; nor did it ſatisfie my very ſences; theſe were tired in the poſſeſſion, and uſe of theſe;
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.8</note> 
                  <hi>The eye is not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in ſeeing, nor the ear in hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:</hi> The neceſſary <hi>novelty</hi> is an undeniable evidence of the <hi>vanity</hi>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:41414:37"/>of theſe delights.
<note place="margin">Sinful.</note> It were well if I could ſay theſe pleaſures were only <hi>ſenſible,</hi> my ſoul hath on wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful experience found them the <hi>pleaſures of ſin;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 11.25.</note> not onely the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, but alſo the <hi>cauſe of ſin:</hi> I never could poſſeſs them without ſin; I have in this reſpect paid full dear for all the pleaſures I have enjoyed under the ſun; they have ſtoln too much of mine heart and affections, they have eaten into, and eaten up too much of my precious time; they have dulled my ſences; ſtupified my ſoul, and diſcompoſed me unto the duties of holineſs; they have been baits and ſnares, whereby I have been entiſed unto, and entangled in ſin, they have diverted my ſoul from ſeeking, and ſolacing it ſelf, in more ſerious and ſatisfying delights: the <hi>ſinfulneſs of my pleaſure</hi> hath eaten out the <hi>ſweetneſs of my plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe pleaſures of ſin are but
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:41414:37"/>
                  <hi>for a ſeaſon;</hi> are often changing,
<note place="margin">Short.</note> and do ſoon vaniſh; will certainly expire; cannot endure for ever, and leave bitterneſs behind them when they go away; they have coſt me more ſmart and greif when they have been ended, then they did afford me joy or content whilſt they continued: I may willingly diſmiſs thoſe pleaſures, which I have bought at ſo dear a rate; poſſeſs ſo uncertainly, and for ſo ſhort a ſeaſon; and proved ſo vain, empty, and diſſatisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
               <p>My Soul! Let me chearfully, contentedly ceaſe from my <hi>plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi> among the living on earth; whilſt I ſhall therein ceaſe from the <hi>ſinning</hi> and <hi>ſorrowing,</hi> neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily attendant on, and inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably annexed unto my pleaſures: and yet conſider, all joy is not at an end with me when I die;
<note place="margin">Joy ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth and yet remaineth</note> I paſs not from all pleaſure, when parted from theſe; I onely leave
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:41414:38"/>what is ſenſible and ſinful; but death ſhall tranſmit my ſoul into Gods preſence, in which are <hi>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of pleaſures for evermore:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 16.11</note> can I think the fulneſs of laſting joys, ſolacing my ſoul in the ſight of God, will not compenſate my loſs of the ſenſible pleaſures of ſin, which are but for a ſeaſon? did theſe caſt the ſcales of <hi>Moſes</hi> judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and affections in his time of life,
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.25, 26, 27.</note> youth and ſtrength, cauſing him to deſpiſe the Crown and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Egypt; and to chuſe afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the people of God, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then to be called the ſon of <hi>Pharoah</hi>'s Daughter? And ſhall not the ſence and expectation thereof make me content to leave the delights, which I cannot longer enjoy? It was my duty to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed them ſooner; I may well be content to relinquiſh them now, I can enjoy them no longer. My ſoul! yeild unto, rejoyce in, and bleſs God for that neceſſity, which
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:41414:38"/>doth enforce thy duty; and will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly leave thoſe pleaſures, which would have left thee in bitterneſs, if thou ſhould longer abide in the body, the onely ſubject capable of theſe ſenſible pleaſures.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IX.</head>
               <p>DEath will deprive me of all my <hi>outward comforts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Death doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive me of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> I have long en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed to ſupply my neceſſity.</note> goods and poſſeſſions in the world, Wife, Children and Servants which mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred to me; Be it ſo; it is Gods mercy I have enjoyed them for <hi>ſo long a time;</hi> I am in the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of them a tenant at Gods will, he doth not the leaſt wrong to take them from me; ſo kind hath God been to me, he hath let me poſſeſs them, whilſt they could do me good, and I had <hi>need of them:</hi> when I am dead they connot mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter to me; I ſhall have neither need nor uſe of any, or all theſe comforts: I may well be content to leave what I ſhall not lack, what I cannot uſe; it is I confeſs a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:41414:39"/>to have them; but it ſpeaketh <hi>imperfection</hi> to have need of them: is it not much better to be in an eſtate of <hi>perfection</hi> without them, then to have theſe comforts to me continued, and my ſelf abide <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Death doth deprive me of ſome comforts;
<note place="margin">Such as content not nor continue.</note> but they are ſuch which afford no true <hi>content;</hi> nor are they of any <hi>continuance:</hi> they are, though the <hi>beſt things under the ſun;</hi> yet at the beſt, they are but <hi>things under the ſun;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccl. 1.1, 2</note> and all things <hi>under the ſun are vanity and vexation of ſpirit:</hi> they give a little, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed but a little content to my ſence; but not any to my ſoul; they were not obtained with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out care, retained without fear; nor will they now be relinquiſhed without greif: I cannot deny them to be <hi>flowers, flowers of beauty and pleaſure;</hi> but I muſt confeſs I ever found them <hi>fading,</hi> and <hi>full of pricks:</hi> I have not enjoyed them
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:41414:39"/>without <hi>vexation;</hi> and if I live longer, I ſhall ere it be long loſe them, and have them taken from me; they all have the wings of the morning, and flye away in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. I can already ſay of ſome, what I ſhall ſoon ſay of the reſt; I had ſervants, truſty and faithful to me; but they are gone:
<note place="margin">My means by my mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry.</note> I had goods yearly renuing my ſtore, but it is taken from me; I had Children, ſweet babes, the cheif of natures bleſſings; but my <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephs</hi> my <hi>Benjamins are not;</hi> mine outward enjoyments have been to me a <hi>Gourde</hi> of refreſhment, and preſent delight;
<note place="margin">Jon. 4.6, 7</note> but a <hi>Jonahs Gourde</hi> of vanity, in the root of which is a worm, which doth and will ſoon make it wither: if I paſs not from my preſent comforts, they will peirce my ſoul with care and fear, and at laſt periſh in mine hand; I may well be content to die from thoſe comforts, which are ſure to die from me; and leave
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:41414:40"/>me in ſorrow, even in <hi>worldly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row which worketh death:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.10.</note> What great difference is it for me to be parted from my comforts, or to have my comforts parted from me? can any thing but a childiſh tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, make me cry, when thoſe pleaſing toyes are taken from me, which I freely leave when tired with them: or which I fling from me with fury when I feel my ſelf hurt by them? what cauſe have I to be thus diſmaied, to be divided from thoſe comforts which I have thus long enjoy'd, to ſupply my need yet with certain dolor, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain durance? ſhall I ſo fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly love, as not be content to leave what loadeth me with care and fear; yet cannot laſt; but will be gone from me, if I ſtay longer in this world?</p>
               <p>Death taketh me from my <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward comforts;</hi> but yet, I leave them to, and for <hi>the comfort of my relations and friends,</hi> which ſtay
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:41414:40"/>behind me; they will have the uſe of them, they will do them good; though I leave them, they are not loſt, my turn is ſerved by them; ſhall I grudge that others have them to ſerve their turn, as they ſerved mine? hath it not been my care to get goods, that I might leave them to my Relations? and ſhall I now be unwilling to leave them that little which I have gotten? and which can now do me no more good?</p>
               <p>Though death deprive me of ſome uſeleſs <hi>moveables;</hi> yet it lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth me my moſt <hi>precious jewels,</hi> and chiefeſt ſubſtance: the <hi>graces of my ſoul,</hi> the glorious priviledges of my faith, death cannot touch, or take from me; and theſe are more worth then all the world: My ſoul! play the Merchant, be content to ſee thy luggage, and empty cask caſt overboard, to ſave thy choice commodities, and thy pearls of price: death may take
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:41414:41"/>me from <hi>riches,</hi> it cannot touch my <hi>righteouſneſs;</hi> it may anticipate my pompous Funeral, but it cannot hinder my graces from going with me to Heaven; though I muſt at death leave my outward comforts, this is mine advantage I may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and carry with me mine <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity:</hi> My ſoul! death ſhall not meddle with thy beſt treaſure; be therefore content to part with thy worſt enjoyments; thine outward comforts: whilſt thy tottering tabernacle muſt fall, thine earthly cottage muſt be burnt; rejoyce, and bleſs God that thou canſt ſave any thing; much more, that thy <hi>beſt goods,</hi> thy <hi>ſubſtance</hi> is eſcaped and ſecured; for being herewith ſtored, thou ſhalt poſſeſs an eſtate much more plentiful and pleaſant, then what thou hadſt in this life and world.
<note place="margin">Death cuts me off from my relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but caſteth them on God.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>SECT. X.</head>
               <p>DEath <hi>will cut me off from my dear Relations,</hi> whoſe depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:41414:41"/>hath been on my care for them; but, it will then diſpoſe them under the more immediate care, protection,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 68.5. Hoſ. 14.3.</note> and providence of God, who is, <hi>judge of the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows caſe, and with whom the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſs find mercy.</hi> It peirceth my ſoul to hear the Wife of my boſom cry, <hi>Oh Husband! What ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of me, when thou the covering of mine eyes art taken from me?</hi> and to hear my Children cry, <hi>What ſhall become of us, when our careful, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate Father is gone?</hi> be ſtill my ſoul! ſubmit, yeild unto my God; even <hi>ſo father,</hi> for <hi>ſo it ſeemeth good unto thee:</hi> Is it not my duty by an act of faith, to <hi>caſt my fatherleſs Children on the Lord?</hi> have I not taught, and often aſſured my Widow, ſhe muſt truſt in God? was it not the Lord who provided for them by me? in vain had I riſen early, gone to bed late, &amp; eaten the bread of carefulneſs, if God had not built my houſe: Shall
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:41414:42"/>I think the ſame God cannot, or ſhall I fear he will not provide for them without me? they may be put upon ſome more ſenſible ſtraits, to exert ſome more ſpecial acts of faith; more eminently to exerciſe ſome graces; but they have the ſame aſſurance, and ſome better ſecurity, that they ſhall enjoy food convenient, the Fountain abideth full and flowing, though not by the ſame pipe and conduit which is cut off: it is Gods property, and promiſe, to take care of the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow and Fatherleſs: eſpecially of ſuch who are ſo made for the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of his truth: Why do I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet my ſelf for the ſadneſs of that condition, which ſetteth my dear Relations in a more ſpecial de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance on God; and ſecureth to them the more peculiar provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God? I love them; I have looked after them whilſt I lived; I will now leave the care of them to him, who expreſſed it
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:41414:42"/>by me; who can and will expreſs the ſame without me; who is charged with them by his own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty and promiſe; who is more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, more eminently bound to look after them, by taking, thus taking me from them.</p>
               <p>O my God! give my Wife and Children a fear of thee; ſubmiſſion to thee; and faith in thee; be thou the Husband of my Widow; and the Father of my fatherleſs Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; that to the praiſe of thee who faileſt not, they may tell the world, the unbeleiving world; they loſt nothing by looſing, thus looſing me: they traded to good advantage, by freely, willingly, cheerfully, contentedly, giving up a moſt loving Husband, and tender Father, to the pleaſure of a gracious, faithful, never failing God; who ſtayeth with them, and careth for them, when he by death doth take me from them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:41414:43"/>
               <head>SECT. XI.</head>
               <p>AFter death,
<note place="margin">Death hindreth me from knowing what is done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſun; and ſo I ſhall know no evil.</note> I muſt <hi>lie down in the pit,</hi> I ſhall be <hi>covered with darkneſs;</hi> I ſhall not <hi>know what is done under the Sun;</hi> This will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed be my ſtate: but yet, whilſt I lie down in the pit, <hi>I ſhall abide in ſafety,</hi> and be delivered from my brethrens rage and fury; My Brother <hi>Reuben</hi> proveth moſt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and affectionate, by letting me down into the pit; he thereby ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cureth, not onely my life, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo my liberty againſt my brethrens malice; their hands cannot then reach me to do me hurt; they cannot draw me thence, to ſell and enſlave me to any <hi>Iſhmaelite,</hi> their envy may enquire for me, but they ſhall not find me; I ſhall be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in ſafety, and preferred to glory, when their entangled ſtate ſhall affect their hearts, and make them with bitterneſs to remember, and confeſs, <hi>they are verily guilty concerning their brother, in that they
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:41414:43"/>ſaw the anguiſh of his ſoul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 42.21.</note> 
                  <hi>when he beſought them, and they would not hear him:</hi> my being put into the pit, is the paſſage to glory God hath determined for his beloved <hi>Joſephs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If <hi>darkneſs</hi> cover me; it doth the better ſuit my ſleeping ſtate, and capacitate me thereunto; light is indeed pleaſant to the eye, but it is perturbing, preventing, when men deſire to ſleep: my gracious God layeth me in the grave, as in an houſe of darkneſs; and as on a bed of ſilence; that my wearied body may the better ſleep and take its reſt; until it ſhall be awakened by his laſt trumpet; which ſhall ſummon me to meet my Lord in glory.</p>
               <p>I have no great cauſe to be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for that,
<note place="margin">Nothing but evil under the ſun to be known.</note> I ſhall <hi>not know what is done under the Sun:</hi> for there can be little done againſt me, after I am dead; nothing that can hurt me: ſuppoſe mens
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:41414:44"/>fooliſh envy ſhould digg up my ſtinking carcaſs, to burn or bury it under the Gallows; they may annoy themſelves, they cannot afflict me: ſure I am, they can do nothing under the Sun, which ſhall concerne me when I am dead; why ſhall I be ſo curious, as to covet the knowledge of other mens affairs? I might poſſibly know ſome <hi>good</hi> by my life; but that will be but very little; but I were therein ſure to know very much evil; and ſuch evil as would and muſt afflict me: whilſt I know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing under the Sun, I ſhall not know the prophaneſs, blaſphemies, impieties, injuſtice, oppreſſions, vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, ſuperſtitions, perfidies, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries, and perſecutions which are done under the Sun, all which would call for, and conſtrain greif in my ſoul, and tears from my eyes; ſeeing I could not know a little good, without knowing ſo much evil; ſhall I not be content to be
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:41414:44"/>freed from a ſo vexatious burden as is the knowledge of things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sun; I hate life,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 2.17.</note> becauſe the work which is wrought under the Sun is greivous unto me, for it is vanity and vexation of ſpirit.</p>
               <p>What if I do not know what is done under the Sun?
<note place="margin">After death I ſhall know much good.</note> I ſhall know much better things: my ſoul the ſeat and ſubject of mine under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, ſhall be acquainted with, and fully apprehend the glories which are above the Sun: I ſhall then know the depths of divine mercy, the myſteries of mans ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation;
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.12.</note> I ſhall then <hi>know as I am known;</hi> I ſhall perfectly know God and Chriſt; ſhall I ſtick to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſuch an exchange of objects to mine underſtanding? is not my loſs great, and greatly to be la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented? by which I onely looſe the knowledge of vanity, which would not make me happy; and iniquity which would make me mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable; but gain the knowledge,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:41414:45"/>the perfect knowledg of good, much good, true and ſubſtantial good, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly good, without the leaſt mixture of evil; and that in an eſtate, in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of perfect glory?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XII.</head>
               <p>AFter death there ſhall be <hi>no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of me:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">No re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of me after death, nor of my ſin.</note> but its no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; <hi>a great name,</hi> fooliſhly purchaſed by the great precipitacie of ſome in the world; is nothing but a <hi>great bub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of vanity,</hi> which will wear out at laſt; time will eat it out of the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt Cities, or marble Monuments: and I hope when I am forgotten, my ſin &amp; ſhame will alſo be forgotten: ſerious thoughts ſuggeſt unto me content, the little good I have done ſhould be forgotten, ſo that my folly and wickedneſs may not be remembred: and yet,</p>
               <p>My ſoul! be not diſmaid, the Scripture doth declare the <hi>memory of the juſt is bleſſed;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 10.7. &amp; 112.6.</note> and the <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſhall be had in everlaſting remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance;</hi> God hath provided that
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:41414:45"/>his peoples names ſhall live, when their dead bodies ſhall conſume in the grave: the Lord hath uſed me whilſt I lived, as an inſtrument of his truth and honour; can I dye, and be forgotten in his Church, or among his people? ſhall not my works follow me? ſhall not my works praiſe me in the gate? can the ſinners by me reproved, or the Saints by me converted to, or confirmed in the truth, remember themſelves, their ſin, or duty, and forget me? God hath bleſſed me with many laſting memorials of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; a fruitful progeny: I need not build tombs, or Cities and call them after my name: for when I am dead my ſons will preſerve the memory of my name: the rotting of the name is a curſe, entailed on men of rotten lives, and is ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily effected by Gods cutting off the budding race, and hopeful progeny: whatever hath befal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len me in this life, God hath not
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:41414:46"/>ſuffered this cauſe procuring, or producing this effect, to be my lot; I will not therefore torment my ſelf with a fear that it ſhould fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me when dead. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding my ſinfulneſs, my care ſhall be that my life and death may make it legible, that my <hi>name is written in the book of life;</hi> and therein I have cauſe to rejoyce, more then if the <hi>devils we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to me:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 10.20</note> I have laid ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d on Gods Covenant; he hath given me a place in his ſanctuary, better then a name of ſons and daughters: my name can never be blotted out of that book; mine intereſt and relation by that covenant ſhall ever be acknowledged, and remembred; I therefore cannot poſſibly be buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in oblivion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XIII.</head>
               <p>DEath will <hi>remove me from my place,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Death wil remove me from my place, but it is movable.</note> that it ſhall know me no more: it will ſo: but ſhall this diſmay me? am not I a pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grim
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:41414:46"/>in this earth as all my fathers were? the Patriarchs paſſed their time on earth in moveable tents, <hi>Looking for a City whoſe founder and maker is God:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 10.10.</note> the houſes in which I have lived, have ſeemed to be more laſting ſtructures; yet they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver were to me any durable ſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; I have not indeed removed my tents, but I have been often removed from my tents: I have ever been in a ſhifting ſtate; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving from one houſe unto another; from one place to another; and this hath been to me very tedious and irkſom: my Father did indeed raiſe many ſtately ſtructures;
<note place="margin">In <hi>Dublin</hi> in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
                  </note> not one of all his ſons poſſeſſed them, or any of them; the brick walls may bear his name, none of his children do or can inhabit them: God hath made conſtant motion my condition; he hath wiſely mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved me from place to place, that I might be in love with no place under the ſun: if I have liked mine
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:41414:47"/>houſe &amp; place never ſo well, I have by one means or other been forced to leave it; and that either becauſe it was none of mine, or elſe mens perſecuting rage would not ſuffer me in peace to poſſeſs it; or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe my Maſters work hath been done in that place and called me to another: How often have I been forcibly removed from people whom I have dearly loved, and from places where I thought I had pitched my tent; and reſolved to reſt? I digged a grave for my children, wherein I intended to have been intombed my ſelf; and yet my dead babes are diſperſed; their graves are at a diſtance each from other; and tis very unlikely my grave ſhould be with any of them. If Death remove me from my place; it doth nothing but what hath been common to me all my life, I will not therefore think it ſtrange once more to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move my place; but will readily,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:41414:47"/>contentedly pack up and be gone; for this remove ſhall be my <hi>laſt remove,</hi> for this remove ſhall be my <hi>beſt remove:</hi> for this remove ſhall move me from Earth to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: and there I have an houſe of mine own; a better houſe then any this world affordeth; <hi>an houſe not made with hands; an eternal houſe; whoſe builder and maker is God;</hi> a Manſion houſe, prepared by Chriſt my precurſor, for to entertain me, and wherein I muſt and ſhall abide for ever; an houſe which time can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not waſte or ruine; nor humane force pull down, or raze; an houſe moſt pleaſantly ſcituated, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated with all conveniencies, exempt from all annoyances, and amply furniſhed with what may make it to me an happy habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; an houſe it is for which I ſhall pay no rent, or taxes; in which I ſhall not live a tenant at will, but I ſhall poſſeſs this houſe fully, freely and for ever; being once
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:41414:48"/>ſettled in it, I ſhall not deſire to leave it; I ſhall not be ſequeſtred out of it; and (that which is worth all) this houſe is mine own houſe, mine inheritance, purchaſed for me by my Saviour, and paſſed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by the gift of my gracious Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, none can diſpute my title, or by an <hi>Ejectione firma,</hi> force me out of my houſe: My ſoul! Shall I not be willing to go to, and live in mine own houſe? and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo well ſcituate, ſo conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently formed, ſo well furniſhed; rather then in a ſtrangers incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient houſe? Shall I not prefer an houſe of Gods building, before the beſt of mans? ſhall I not chuſe an eternal, rather then a decayed, falling, ruinous habitation? My ſoul! be not troubled at this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move; <hi>thou beleiveſt in God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive alſo in Chriſt;</hi> he hath ſaid, <hi>in his Fathers Houſe are many manſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 14.1, 2.</note> 
                  <hi>if it were not ſo he would have told us;</hi> he is gone before to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:41414:48"/>a place for his removing people; ſhall I not up and after, ſuch an harbinger? to poſſeſs the glorious manſions of his moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious proviſion?</p>
               <p>Why is my remove by death my terror? my trouble? this remove will tranſmit me into a ſtation, not more permanent then glorious: I am removing to a better houſe; yea, to poſſeſs a <hi>KINGDOM:</hi> A Kingdom, not like the Kingdoms of this world; not a narrow, empty, envied, diſtracted, divided, ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, ſinful, tranſient, and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Kingdom; not a Kingdom ſubject to wars, tumults, fire, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, peſtilence, ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation; and yet with ambition men do ſeek, with joy they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move into, with difficulty and danger they obtain theſe miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble earthly Kingdoms: but my Kingdom, to which I ſhall paſs, is a ſpiritual, heavenly, unſhaken, united, ample, abundant, unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:41414:49"/>undiſturbed, peaceable and everlaſting Kingdom; not ſubject to any invaſion or uſurpation; to any confuſion or commotions; to any mutations or violent revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; to any alteration or dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
               <p>Seeing it is the will of my heavenly Father to give me a Kingdom; ſuch a Kingdom; and my Kingdom is not of this world; why ſhould I be unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to leave this world, and to go to my Kingdom? will any Prince deſire to live out of that Kingdom to which he is heir? Since O my God! thou haſt given me a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; give me a ſpirit fit for, and deſirous of this thy Kingdom; Let me live, and dye worthy the hopes of thine heavenly Kingdom; let not this beggarly, and theſe baſe appendants make me draw back when called to paſs into my King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: Up my ſoul; enter this ſtrait gate into thy royal Manſion; ſtoop under this croſs that thou mayſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:41414:49"/>the crown of righteouſneſs, and life; the incorruptible crown of glory: ambition maketh men, whoſe portion is in this life, moſt deſperately daring, to adventure their all for a poor Cottage-King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, ſubject to commotion: ſhall not grace make me much more willing to put off my natural life; that I may put on this living im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marceſſible Crown, which cannot ſit on a mortal head? and to paſs from an houſe of bondage, through a red Sea, to a land of reſt and pleaſure; a ſtation permanent; and to a Kingdom of glory? I will cheerfully remove this once; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I ſhall remove to ſo great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage; and after this I ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move no more.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XIV.</head>
               <p>DEath will <hi>take me from off my work;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Death wil end my work yea and my day.</note> after it Chriſts Church ſhall enjoy no benefit by <hi>my Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry;</hi> I muſt now, <hi>no longer labour in the Lords Vineyard:</hi> It is very
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:41414:50"/>true; and this cannot but reduce me to a ſtrait, and put me to a ſtand what to chuſe; for if I live in the fleſh, the Church will reap the fruit of my labour; that <hi>I abide in the fleſh is for them more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 1.22, 23.</note> nevertheleſs, for me, <hi>to dye is gain;</hi> I ſhall be hereby eaſed of the charge and care of immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſouls; of the pains and burden of my Miniſtry; of the fear and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers which attend my duty; of the toil and travel of all my labour; and of the tiring brunt of my working day; all which have made me often wiſh, my day were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and that my night were come; <hi>There are twelve hours in the day,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 11.9.</note> 
                  <hi>wherein men work, and then commeth the night, wherein no man worketh:</hi> My day is not mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by my work, but my work is proportioned to my day; though I could by my natural ſtrength; I cannot work longer for lack of time; when my day is done, my
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:41414:50"/>work is done; and ſhall I not be content with the end of both? if my Maſter eaſe me of my burthen by ending my day, have I any cauſe to murmur? and yet,</p>
               <p>The hinderance of my work ſhall be no hinderance to my wages:
<note place="margin">Wages ſhall be ſure.</note> my two talents, well improved for a little time, may approve me faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full when my maſter commeth;
<note place="margin">Matth. 25.22, 23. and 20.9.</note> and ſo will paſs me into my Maſters joy, as certainly, as if I had traded with ten talents, and for a longer time: he who worketh in my Lords Vineyard but one hour, ſhall receive his penny, as well as he who hath endured the heat and brunt of the day: I have all my days ſtretched forth my hands to a ſtiffnecked and ſtuborn generation, who would not hear; mens obdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy hath made my miniſtry a work of difficulty and danger; I have in it been often tyred, and willing to lye down and reſt; yet I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver durſt look back, nor take my
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:41414:51"/>hand from the Plough, on which my God hath layed it; but I ſhall now find my <hi>recompence is with the Lord, and my reward is with my God,</hi> ſhall I repine to go to him to receive it? I will rejoyce I have been ſo long ſerviceable in Gods Church, and an inſtrument to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie him on earth; and it ſhall be my joy, that I muſt now ceaſe from my labour, go home to my Maſter, and be glorified with him in the heavens.</p>
               <p>I ſhall when dead, labour no more in the Lords Vineyard; but I ſhall now drink my ſelf drunk of the fruit of his Vine, with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in his Kingdom: I ſhall no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſerve God on earth; but from henceforth I ſhall ſing praiſes to him for ever in the heavens: though the Church militant muſt looſe my labour; it ſhall not looſe my ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters care, he will thruſt forth other labourers into his Vineyard; and the Church triumphant will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:41414:51"/>my <hi>company</hi> to enforce their <hi>cry;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 6.10</note> 
                  <hi>How long Lord, before thou wilt avenge our blood on thoſe who dwell on the earth?</hi> come Lord Jeſus, come quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: I have done the work of my ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration; what can I do, or deſire to do more? I have diſpatched the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs charged on my hand; ſhall I be unwilling to ſit ſtill and take mine eaſe? I have delivered the embaſſie, to me committed; ſhall I not willingly return at my Lords command? My ſoul! bleſs God that he would employ weak, worth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs me, and that I have done ſo much, and ſuch work in his houſe, as I have done; Let me be no leſs willing to reſt, and take my eaſe, then to work at my maſters bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XV.</head>
               <p>DEath will <hi>diſſolve my being;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Death diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolveth my being, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chargeth my bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</note> when I am dead, <hi>I am not:</hi> but it will alſo diſcharge my bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den; when I am not, I am not greived: my ſelf, my ſin, and my
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:41414:52"/>ſorrow, ſhall all ceaſe together, and at once, better therefore is the day of my death, then the day of my birth: through all my life I have found little, very little that is deſireable; but much, which I may well ſpare; very much where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I may deſire to be eaſed; for the diſcharge hereof I may well bid death welcome.</p>
               <p>What hath been my whole life, but an eſtate of ſin, ſorrow, of pain and travel; a condition, full of cares, fears, greifs, tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, afflictions, croſſes, loſſes, perſecutions, reproaches, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and great diſtreſſes, ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and ſinful weakneſſes, and ſoul-perplexities? <hi>man that is born of a woman,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 5.7.</note> 
                  <hi>is born unto trouble, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the ſparks flye upward:</hi> theſe are ſo natural to me, and inherent i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> me, that they exiſt in, and ſubſiſt with my very ſelf; I cannot be and be without them; I cannot lay them down, without laying
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:41414:52"/>my ſelf aſide: vanity, vexation, and trouble, qualifie my life as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeperable to it; why am I perplexed with an apprehenſion that ſuch a life draweth to a period? I have all my days been perſecuted by hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane rage and power, and ſo ſhould be ſtill if I live longer; I may well be contented to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved into an eſtate of peace: when men have killed my body, they have done their worſt, their all; they have me not to inſult over; they do much better for me then they are aware of; they give me a writ of eaſe from all my travel, and trouble; in the grave the <hi>wicked do and ſhall ceaſe from troubling;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 3.17, 18.</note> 
                  <hi>the weary ſhall be at reſt; the priſoners do reſt toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and they hear not the voice of the oppreſſor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My ſoul! were there no more in death, but this releaſe from greif, pain, ſorrow and travel; thou mayeſt well reſign me up to
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:41414:53"/>the ſtroak of death; I may be content not to be, that ſo I may not be ſo miſerable; well may death be ſweet to me, to whom my whole life hath been ſo bitter: how many have deſired death, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the danger, diſtreſs, and dolour of their lives? how many have ſinfully deſtroyed their lives, to deliver themſelves from their cares, fears, greifs, wants, and woful pains? I deſire not, I dare not, I will not tempt God, and murmur againſt his providence, by haſtening my death, by a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, untimely, unlawful, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural act of ſelf-violence; <hi>all the days of mine appointed time, I will wait till my change come;</hi> but I may very cheerfully, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, yeild unto that ſtroak which is ſent of God to eaſe me of ſo great a burden: the rather, becauſe Death is my diſcharge from <hi>ſin,</hi> as well as from <hi>ſorrow;</hi> and death onely can be the diſcharge thereof:
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:41414:53"/>
                  <hi>In iniquity I was conceived,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.5.</note> 
                  <hi>in ſin did my Mother bring me forth;</hi> ſin is to me as natural as my ſelf; it is inherent in my being; it was born with me; it hath grown up with my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ody; that will not, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be divided from this; this corruptible body, is the uphold of the body of corruption; theſe two do ſtand, and will fall together: This dying fleſh is not only the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of ſence, but alſo the ſeat of ſin; the members of my body, are the inſtruments of ſin, unto, and until death: how tormenting hath life been unto my ſoul, by reaſon of temptation unto ſin? the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant militation of my fleſh, hath made my life a continual conflict: how have I feared to nouriſh my body, becauſe thereby I made pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for the fleſh to fulfil the luſts thereof? I could never yet tame ſin, but by buffetting my fleſh, and by abſtracting from the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of my being.</p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:41414:54"/>
               <p>I cannot be rid of ſin, till I be releaſed of life: Oh the care to avoid, fear to commit ſin, to which I have been ſubject! how many times have I been forced to embrace ſorrow, to ſhun ſin? and to ſit alone, expoſed to ſcorn and miſery, becauſe I durſt not run to the exceſs of riot with other men? Mortification of ſin, hath been the main of my buſineſs, ſince I ſaw the ſinfulneſs of ſin: and yet do I what I could, it would and doth exiſt in me, and prevail upon me; to the often checking my comforts; hindring my communion with God; and wounding my conſcience by omiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of, and defects in duty; by commiſſion of hainous ſins, and many abberrations from my hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly father, forced to fetch me home by paternal caſtigation: though Gods grace hath maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in me a conſtant militation, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſin could not reign in my morta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:41414:54"/>body; and my Father hath ever kept me under the rod of correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; yet, the law in my members hath rebelled againſt the law in my mind; and led me captive unto ſin: the beſt of my life hath been a candid confeſſion, and a continual complaint, <hi>that the good I would do I do not, and the evil I would not do, that I do;</hi> and an affectionate outcry; <hi>Oh wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliver me from this body of ſin?</hi> I muſt, I may whilſt I live, make it my care to keep under my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, leſt my ſin overcome me; and yet whilſt I abide in the body, I ſhall bear about a body of corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; the death of this ſhall be, and it onely can be the deſtruction of that: Onely in the grave I ſhall ceaſe to ſin; when I am not, I ſhall not be ſinful; I ſhall not be a ſinner.</p>
               <p>My Soul! Doſt thou deſire to be freed from the ſuggeſtions,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:41414:55"/>temptations, and inclinations to ſin? and yet tremble at the thoughts of diſſolution, which will, and onely can deliver thee from them all? be aſſured after death thou ſhalt not be greived for, becauſe thou ſhalt not be ſtained with thy daily guilt: thy ſinful nature ſhall then no more greive the Spirit of thy holy God: Haſt thou waged a mortal warfare againſt thy ſin, all my life? and wilt thou now give back in the laſt mortal ſtroak? though this fall upon thy ſelf with ſome violence, it will certainly give thee the full conqueſt over thy luſts with which thou haſt ſo long conteſted; fall willingly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that fall, which will make thee full victor over theſe curſed <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Come O my ſoul! be willing to ſtoop that thou mayſt lay down thy load; ſubmit freely to that ſtroak, which will for ever ſet thee free from all ſin, and from all ſorrow:
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:41414:55"/>ceaſe to complain that thy life hath been tedious, and tireſom, trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and toilſom; or ſhew thy ſelf content and truly glad to be eaſed: deſire to be diſſolved, that thy burden of ſin and ſorrow may be diſcharged. Be ſtill O my ſoul! the ſtroke of death is dreadful; but it once ſtruck, doth for ever diſmiſs and deſtroy the ſuggeſtions of Satan, the motions of ſin, the actings of unrighteouſneſs, the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of Gods wrath, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions by mens rage and envy, with all other evils: who would not bear ſome dread to be deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from ſo great diſtreſs; when I am dead, I ſhall ceaſe from my labour; <hi>I ſhall reſt from mine own works</hi> of ſin and ſorrow; theſe are indeed moſt properly mine own works; produced, procured by my ſelf; created, continued by, and with my ſelf; acted by, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtent in, and with my ſelf; to be only deſolved and deſtroyed with
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:41414:56"/>my ſelf: whilſt I am, I am as, yea, above others of my brethren, the Butt of Satans rage, and mens ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice; the ſubject of ſtrong paſſions and finful motions: whilſt I have lived, I have not done duty to God without great defect; I have not delivered my Maſters meſſage among men, without great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; Satan hath hunted me into ſin, and wicked men hath hunted me into ſufferings; they have lien in wait for me; they have labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to make my tongue my trap, and to enſnare me by my words: but I may now be content, theſe can follow me no further; they ſhall now loſe the ſent; the grave ſhall be my burrough, in it I ſhall be quiet; I ſhall then be out of the reach of luſt, care, trouble, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, ſickneſs, temptation and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution; I ſhall now no more be heard to grieve or groan: I will therefore be willing to ceaſe to be, that <hi>I</hi> may ceaſe to be the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:41414:56"/>ſubject of ſo bad, ſo ſinful quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XVI.</head>
               <p>DEath will <hi>deſtroy my body:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Death de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyeth the body but not the ſoul.</note> be it ſo: that is all it can do; it hath nothing to do with my ſoul, that remaineth <hi>immortal;</hi> it ſhall be ſaved, and ſet in <hi>Abrahams boſom,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n eternal happineſs, as ſoon as it is out of my body; it ſhall be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociated to the <hi>ſpirits of juſt men made perfect:</hi> What need I care how it goeth with my worſer, whilſt I have ſecured, and it goeth ſo well with my better part? my ſoul is an immortal being; out of the reach of humane rage, and the ſtroke of death: What if men and death kill my body, if God will not caſt my ſoul into hell, I eſcape well, and much better then I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve; for ſin had ſhipwracked me both ſoul and body; <hi>I</hi> had forfeit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed both to divine Juſtice: my ſoul being ſaved, <hi>I live in death:</hi> O bleſſed paradox! oh happy ſtate <hi>I
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:41414:57"/>not to dye in dying!</hi> My body is but an <hi>earthen veſſel;</hi> I need not be much troubled if this be broken; ſo that my <hi>heavenly treaſure</hi> be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured and preſerved: my body is onely the <hi>cabinet,</hi> I ſee no great cauſe to be troubled if that be loſt, whilſt the <hi>jewel</hi> of my ſoul is ſafe; <hi>Paul</hi> might well call on the Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to be of good chear in the tempeſt, which tare their tackling and ſunk their ſhip, being able to aſſure them,
<note place="margin">Acts 27.</note> 
                  <hi>no mans life ſhould be loſt but the ſhip onely:</hi> I travel with my ſoul through briars and thorns, ſhall I wonder that I am pricked, and that my cloaths are rent off me? My ſoul is of ſuch value, that all is to be adventured and thrown over-board for its ſalvation; <hi>What ſhall it profit a man if he gain the whole world and loſe his own ſoul?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth: 16.26.</note> my body is dear to me; I will do what I can to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it; but my ſoul is much dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; this muſt be defended by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:41414:57"/>my body to danger and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; skin for skin, riches, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, pleaſures, peace, all my natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral comforts, and outward bleſſings, I would give for my life, but theſe, and life and all will I give for my ſoul:
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.18.</note> My ſoul is redeemed not with <hi>corruptible things, as ſilver and gold; but with the precious blood of Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> Chriſt laid down his life to redeem my ſoul; and ſhall not I willingly lay down my life to keep my redeemed ſoul? O thou the Shepherd and Biſhop of my ſoul, keep it within thy ſheepfold, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till thou ſhalt lead it unto thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; I will not then be ſolicitous, what may befall or become of my body, ſeeing I am under a neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſuffering loſs; I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce that my loſs is not greater; ſuch as might have undone me for ever: welcome death to my body; temporal death which conſiſteth with the life and immortality of my ſoul; and paſſeth it into the fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:41414:58"/>of eternal life: my ſoul may be ſaved by, and under the loſs of my body; but my body could not be ſaved if my ſoul were loſt: Oh ſtrange! Oh bleſſed trade! the loſs I am like to ſuſtain, is mine infinite gain; this loſs of my body ſhall ſave my ſoul; for in the cauſe of Chriſt and his Church, he who would <hi>ſave his life muſt loſe it.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 16.25</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XVII.</head>
               <p>DEath will <hi>ſeperate my ſoul from my body;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Death ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perateth ſoul and body, but not me and God.</note> it will ſo: but it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>ſeperate me from God;</hi> and that was the deſign of death; it cannot ſeperate either the one or the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the love of God in Chriſt Jeſus; <hi>I am perſwaded nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther life, nor death, nor Angels, nor principalities, nor powers, nor things preſent,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.38, 39.</note> 
                  <hi>nor things to come, nor any other creature ſhall be able to ſeperate us from the love of God, which is in Chrict Jeſus our Lord:</hi> ſhall not this inſeperable love to
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:41414:58"/>me, meet with an anſwerable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of love from me? and make me with confidence and reſolution conclude <hi>tribulation, nor diſtreſs, nor perſecution, nor famine, nor nakedneſs, nor peril, nor ſword, ſhall not ſeperate Chriſt from me?</hi> as it is written, <hi>for thy ſake are we killed all the day long, and accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as ſheep to the ſlaughter;</hi> love is a principle of union; it cleaveth to, and looketh after its object, in its moſt low eſtate, and loſt condition. Death ſhall not make me to be deſpiſed or forſaken by my God; <hi>This God is my God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 48.14.</note> 
                  <hi>my God for ever and ever, and he will be my guide unto death;</hi> yea, in, and through the vail of the ſhadow of death, <hi>his rod and his staff ſhall comfort me:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">and 23.4.</note> the Lord his eſteem of, and relation to my ſoul and body, abideth as well, and as much, (though not by the ſame acts and expreſſions of affection) now they are ſeperated from, as
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:41414:59"/>whilſt they were united each unto other: God doth triumphantly obſerve the faith and patience, by which I endure the tearing of them each from other; for the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his truth: he doth diſpatch his Angels to attend my death; and to conveigh my ſoul into <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams boſome,</hi> to the immediate enjoyment of himſelf: nor doth he diſregard my body, when di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided from my ſoul; or diſeſteem the duſt thereof; he cauſeth it to be mourned over by my friends, and natural relations, and to be buried with the greateſt ſolemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, poor, they can obſerve; yea, he loveth it, and looketh on it as uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Chriſt, though laid in the grave, or diſperſed on the earth; <hi>all my members are written in Gods book,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. 139.16</note> not one of them muſt be loſt or miſcarrie; they ſhall not be neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected: my duſt is precious in Gods ſight, not a grain of it ſhall be loſt after it is ſown in the earth
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:41414:59"/>it ſhall moſt certainly ſpring up as precious ſeed; watered with the dew of heaven; the word of the Lord to <hi>Zion,</hi> and all her ſons doth aſſure them and me, that <hi>her dead men ſhall live; together with his dead body they ſhall ariſe; awake and ſing ye that dwell in the duſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 26.19.</note> 
                  <hi>for thy dew, is as the dew of herbs, and the earth ſhall caſt out the dead.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My body remaineth <hi>Gods Jewel,</hi> when it hath loſt that luſtre the ſoul did give it; God locketh it up in the grave as in his cabinet: God well knoweth my body is lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to danger, in the day of his wrath againſt the inhabitants of the earth: the grave is the recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacle from diſtreſs whereinto he doth gather it: know my ſoul and body, you when divided, do abide objects of Gods compaſſion, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placency, and care; <hi>enter into your chambers,</hi> though dark; qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly ſhut your doors about you;
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:41414:60"/>the wiſe God is willing to hide you for a little moment, until his indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation be paſt.</p>
               <p>My ſoul and body are <hi>dear com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions;</hi> it is not ſtrange to ſee theſe two parted with dread, and greif: and yet, neareſt relations, deareſt friends muſt ſhake parting hands each with other in this world; brethren that have lived long toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and love moſt dearly, muſt leave each others company at their Fathers pleaſure; and for their fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture good: this is my caſe in death: my ſoul! be contented; take chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful leave of thy body, thou art re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to the <hi>father of ſpirits.</hi> My body! conſent willingly to ſhake hands, and ſhut out thy ſoul; thou muſt for a time be ſhut up by God, from falling under thoſe deſperate dangers, and deep di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes, which are more dreadful, and intollerable, then is death it ſelf.</p>
               <p>The deſign of death, in divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:41414:60"/>my ſoul from my body, was to <hi>divide both from God:</hi> but this is impoſſible: for union with Chriſt and with God in him, is inſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; no caſe will make them caſt me off; no condition can cut me off from them; <hi>whom they love once they love to the end,</hi> forever.
<note place="margin">Joh. 13.1.</note> Chriſts union is with me; my ſelf; my whole ſelf; the whole, not any ſingle part of man; no part of me, can therefore be by the power of death diſmembred from him: death may militate againſt Chriſts body, it may rend and mangle his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; but it cannot deſtroy his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, his myſtical body; it cannot divide any his members, nor any part of his members from him: death ſhall ere it be long, by the ſound of the laſt triumphant trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, at the glorious and general reſurrection, know, and prove, that the <hi>union between Chriſt, and the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of his people,</hi> is as <hi>real,</hi> as <hi>inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perable;</hi> as the union between him
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:41414:61"/>and their ſouls: Chriſt will not loſe any part of his purchaſe; he paid a price for man; for whole man; for our bodies; and for our ſouls; both are his: all enemies that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt the union; that intercept the communion which is between Chriſt and his members, muſt be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, and the laſt enemy to be ſubdued is death: when the Grave, the Sea, and Hell ſhall give up the dead bodies which are in them, as in repoſitories for a time, I ſhall then find the deſign of death in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding my ſoul, from my body, is failed, diſappointed, and become fruſtrate; it never could divide either of them from God my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or from Jeſus Chriſt my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer: nor ſhall it be able long to keep theſe parts of me aſunder, and at diſtance each from other; for my union with God and Chriſt, doth neceſſitate; and will moſt powerfully, irreſiſtably effect the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>union of my ſoul and body, at the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:41414:61"/>reſurrection; that I, whole I, my ſelf, out only part of my ſelf, may enjoy them for ever.</p>
               <p>Let my God, and my Saviour, do with me what they pleaſe; ſo they will but pleaſe to be with me in life, and in death, whilſt I am: and with my divided parts when I am not; I will then perſwade, prevail with my ſelf, contentedly to enjoy them in my divided parts; until the time return, that my parts reunied, my whole ſelf, may be placed in an inſeperable poſſeſſion of them, in perfect glory, world without end.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XVIII.</head>
               <p>VVHen I am dead my body <hi>will be covered with worms;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Worms will eat me when dead, but conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence will not bite me.</note> and will feed upon me: but it is no matter; I ſhall not ſee their ſcraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; I ſhall not feel their gnaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of my fleſh: and if I did; yet that is nothing, whilſt my ſoul ſhall eſcape the gnawings of an <hi>accuſing conſcience,</hi> that <hi>worm which never dieth:</hi> there is more mercy in being
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:41414:62"/>freed from this one worm, then from many thouſands of thoſe ſilly, weak, dying wormes.</p>
               <p>Why ſhould it trouble me to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the companion of wormes? muſt not I ſay unto the worm, <hi>thou art my Mother,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 17.14</note> 
                  <hi>and my Siſter?</hi> what am I my ſelf, but a worm? a weak creeping worm?
<note place="margin">Pſa. 22.6.</note> 
                  <hi>David</hi> did apprehend himſelf a worm; a King and yet a worm; and <hi>Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dad, Jobs</hi> friend, noteth of man in general,
<note place="margin">Job 25.6.</note> that he is a worm: whilſt I then am my ſelf but a worm, let the worms feed ſweetly upon their fellow: when I am dead I can do man no good; why ſhould I not be glad any creatures can fare the better for my death? the wormes cannot cover me from the ſight of God; they may crawl upon my body; but it is not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by made loathſom to the Lord. They may devour my fleſh; but the worm which never dieth, ſhall not diſtreſs my ſoul; I will not
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:41414:62"/>therefore appear ſo weak as to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict my ſelf, with the apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the power and prevalency of thoſe ſilly creatures; to which I muſt be ſubject, but of which I ſhall not be ſenſible.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XIX.</head>
               <p>IN Death I ſhall <hi>ſee corruption;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In death I ſhall corrupt, but riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</note> my body will corrupt; be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with diſhonour; conſume away to duſt; moulder away to nothing: this I cannot deny; for it was peculiar to the holy one, the Lord Chriſt, and to him onely, to dye, and <hi>not to ſee corruption:</hi> but yet, I do beleive the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of my body: God can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve my duſt, and make my dead bones to live: my body is united unto Chriſt, death cannot deſtroy that union; my body united to Chriſt, ſhall by the power of his reſurrection be moſt certainly raiſed up at the laſt day; that I may ſit with him in heavenly places.</p>
               <p>God is the God of <hi>Abraham,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:41414:63"/>Iſaac,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 22.32</note> and <hi>Jacob;</hi> he is the <hi>God of the living, and not of the dead:</hi> though therefore the bodies of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> be dead, and buried, and have ſeen corruption; and be diſſolved into nothing; yet, they ſhall live a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; they retain in the grave, an animating principle, which will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce its effect; they ſhall be raiſed up; and exiſt in their indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidual, ſpecifical perſons; and ſubſiſtencies: this was the Lords Argument to convince the <hi>Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces</hi> of the <hi>reſurrection of the body;</hi> this priviledge was not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to thoſe Patriarchs; for I alſo <hi>beleive that my redeemer liveth; and that he ſhall at the latter day ſtand upon the earth;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 19.25, 26, 27.</note> 
                  <hi>and though after this skin, wormes deſtroy my body; yet in my fleſh I ſhall ſee God; him I ſhall ſee for my ſelf; whom mine eyes ſhall behold; and not anothers, though my reins be conſumed within me:</hi> My preſent
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:41414:63"/>life doth witneſs the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> to be a <hi>living ſoul;</hi> my reſurrection from death, and the grave, muſt witneſs the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> to be a <hi>quickening ſpirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My body is part of my ſelf; it muſt not, it cannot be loſt: its ſeperation from my ſoul, maketh me ceaſe to be; this ſeperation continued, would continue me a nonentity for ever; <hi>my ſelf</hi> is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed and related to the Lord; and my ſoul, or my body is rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him, but as parts of <hi>my ſelf;</hi> theſe divided muſt be reuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that <hi>my ſelf</hi> may exiſt to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy my redemption by him, and my relation to him: though the Lords ſpecial care is for my ſoul, as my better and more noble part; he hath not excluded, he doth not deſpiſe, he will not neglect my body: My ſoul, and body are now joynt ſubjects of grace, they muſt therefore hereafter be joynt ſubjects of glory: they have in
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:41414:64"/>this world been joynt agents o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> duty to God; and joynt patients in dolour for God; they muſt therefore in the world to come be joynt heirs of dignity; and joynt poſſeſſors of comfort from the Lord.</p>
               <p>After all the changes which ſhall or can paſs, and return upon my body; God will gather up my duſt; bring together my ſcattered bones; raiſe up this very body, and reunite it to this very ſoul: my body which ſhall corrupt and conſume to nothing, ſhall be raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the <hi>very ſame for ſubſtance,</hi> that it now is; but it ſhall then be cloathed with more excellent qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, moſt ſuitable to the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of my ſoul; in that eſtate of glory, it ſhall be raiſed up to enjoy: my body is now ſown in <hi>corruption,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.42, 43, 44.</note> but it ſhall be raiſed in <hi>incorruption;</hi> it is ſown in <hi>diſhonour,</hi> it ſhall be raiſed in <hi>Glory:</hi> it is ſown in weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, it ſhall be raiſed in power:
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:41414:64"/>it is ſown a <hi>natural body,</hi> it ſhall be raiſed a <hi>ſpiritual body:</hi> what then do I looſe by having my body for a time reſolved into nothing; conſumed into duſt? I looſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the enjoyment of my ſelf, for a little ſeaſon; which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing expired I ſhall return and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enjoyn my ſelf to very much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage: doth not the Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man joy to ſee his ſeed rot in the ground? becauſe he hopeth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the ſame body with better qualities: ſhall not I through grace, be willing to be reſolved into nothing, that I may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored better? O fool!
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.36.</note> 
                  <hi>no ſeed is quickened unleſs it firſt dye;</hi> my ſoul, reſiſt not the pleaſure, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke not the order of my Maker: if he kill to make alive; diſſolve that he may reſtore my body, with the moſt bleſſed change of quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, to the ſame ſubſtance; wilt thou diſpute or decline his will? come, be content; cheerfully
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:41414:65"/>ſhake hands with my body; and let it go; leave it; look no more af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it; though it be loſt from thee, it is not loſt from God or Chriſt; nor is it loſt for ever: when Chriſt ſhall appear, I <hi>my ſelf</hi> ſhall, my <hi>whole ſelf,</hi> conſiſting of ſoul and body,
<note place="margin">Col. 3.4.</note> ſhall appear with him in glory, for he will raiſe me from the dead,
<note place="margin">Phil. 3.2.</note> and change my vile body; that it may be faſhioned like unto his glorious body.</p>
               <p>I cannot but pray, that God would deliver me, my body; from wicked men, who are his ſword, his hand, to cut it down, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce it into nothing; yet my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>not my will, but thy will be done;</hi> I will ſubmit; I will be content; <hi>I will wait my appointed time, till my change ſhall come;</hi> and I will retain the confidence, and poſſeſs my ſoul in the comfortable expectation of my reſurrection; for as for me, <hi>I ſhall behold thy face in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 17.15.</note> 
                  <hi>I ſhall be ſatisfied, when
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:41414:65"/>I awake, and ariſe in thy likeneſs.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XX.</head>
               <p>DEath is that dreadful gulf,
<note place="margin">Death en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> into eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it is of good.</note> which once ſhot, lancheth mine immortal ſoul into the ocean of <hi>Eternity:</hi> Eternity! what is that? a word of aſtoniſhment! an eſtate of amazement! I cannot look into it without heart-ſinking thoughts, ſoul-troubling apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: It is a depth unfathomable; a length and breath immeaſurable; an height undiſcernable; a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance undeterminable, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exſpirable: but yet, <hi>Eternity</hi> is in all theſe reſpects, an eſtate moſt proper to mine immortal ſoul: herein an <hi>eternal</hi> ſubject, ſhall ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace it ſelf, in its <hi>eternal</hi> object un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all <hi>Eternity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Times return hath been the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation of my life,
<note place="margin">Times re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn is trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome.</note> becauſe it was the limitation of my comforts: were mine eſtate never ſo pleaſant to me in reſpect of my health, wealth, plenty, peace, friends and
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:41414:66"/>familiars, or the like enjoyments; the diſcernable approaching peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od of them, hath bidden a ſtand to my delight in them; and damped mine affections towards them: <hi>The things which are ſeen are temporal, but the things which are not ſeen are eternal:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.18.</note> ſenſual pleaſures have the wings of the morning, they paſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with time; but <hi>Eternity</hi> is an adjunct, a property which ſtamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no mean degree of excellency, on thoſe glorious inviſible objects, which are propoſed to our faith; to counterpoiſe thoſe viſible but temporal good things, which cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivate our ſence.</p>
               <p>My ſoul! in <hi>Eternity</hi> thou ſhalt not be tired, with telling the flee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting hours; with obſerving the rerurning days, moneths or years: thine expectation of good or evil ſhall not then be tedious: thou ſhalt be by death tranſported and reſolved into perfect, full, and for ever enjoyment of perfect good:
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:41414:66"/>and that without alteration, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree; without encreaſe or diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; without conſumption or expiration: Thou ſhalt now poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs an everlaſting noon day; thy ſun ſhall no more riſe, nor ſet; time ſhall be to thee no more; thine autumne ſhall abide freſh and green, fair and fruitful, without the leaſt change by the encreaſing reviving ſpring, or by the chilling, clouding, killing winter: thy ſtars ſhall not be clouded, thy moon ſhall know no changes in this eſtate of <hi>Eternity:</hi> There ſhall be no Sun, Moon or Stars; thou ſhalt not need, and therefore thou ſhalt not have thoſe directions, and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations of time; for thy day ſhall abide in its perpetual bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, without any dawning, or the leaſt approach of night.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eternity</hi> exiſteen not in it ſelf:
<note place="margin">Eternity an adjunct to the beſt things.</note> it is a property which paſſeth on ſome condition: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> adjunct quality which ſtandeth not alone, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſteth
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:41414:67"/>in its ſubject. My ſoul look unto, and ſecure the ſubject, then wilt thou ſoon ſee, that <hi>Eternity</hi> is a quality greatly deſirable; an adjunct unto thy great advantage; when death ſhall determine thy days it ſhall lanch thee into; but it ſhall not leave thee fluctuating on the uncertain waves of <hi>Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> for the ſpirit goeth unto God who gave it; and as the tree fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſo it lieth; thou ſhalt moſt certainly be ſet in that eſtate, which muſt be thine <hi>Eternal eſtate,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any poſſibility of alteration, or expiration: thou by death ſaileſt into the ſea of <hi>Elernity;</hi> or rather thou paſſeſt through the red ſea, unto the reſting, refreſhing ſhores of <hi>eternal ſalvation,</hi> an eternal <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance,</hi> eternal <hi>glory,</hi> and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>life:</hi> theſe are the bleſſed ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in which thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Eternity</hi> muſt and ſhall exiſt: Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> thou not in this life taſted the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>weetneſs of thoſe objects? haſt thou not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:41414:67"/>theſe as that ſilver bell, for which thou haſt run the race of righteouſneſs? are not theſe the recompence of reward at which thou haſt looked, as thine encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to all thy travel, and in all thy trouble; in expectation of theſe, I have deſpiſed the ſhame, and endured the croſs: can I chuſe but deſire theſe ſhould be? can I chuſe but leap for joy to know that theſe inviſible things are <hi>eternal?</hi> My ſoul, ſtand ſtill upon thy dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhore, take a ſecond, a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious view of <hi>eternity,</hi> as affixed to thy <hi>ſalvation</hi> to thine <hi>inheritance,</hi> to thy <hi>glory,</hi> and to thy <hi>life,</hi> and tremble, be troubled at the thoughts thereof if thou canſt; thou wilt be more ready to tumble thy ſelf headlong into, then once to turn back from thine <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt then,
<note place="margin">Eternal ſalvation.</note> Death determineth all my woe; it giveth me an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity from all evil; it paſſeth me
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:41414:68"/>into the poſſeſſion of <hi>ſalvation:</hi> ſalvation from ſin, from ſorrow, from weakneſs, from ſickneſs, from all defects, and deformities, from all infirmities and imperfections, from diſeaſes of body, diſgrace un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my name, and diſtempers of mind; from all the envy of Satan, rage of men, and wrath of God; is the happy and certain ſequel of my death through Chriſt my Lord. Can it poſſibly greive or amaze me to ſee, and to know <hi>that this ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is eternal?</hi> or that I am going to poſſeſs and enjoy it for ever? ſhall my heart ake to apppre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend it ſhall never ake more? ſhall I blear mine eyes with weeping, becauſe God is about to wipe all tears from mine eyes for ever? Have not I beleived and preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this <hi>ſalvation,</hi> and the <hi>eternity</hi> thereof? ſhall now mine entrance thereinto, be mine affliction? I have profeſſed, my ſelf did and would, and I have earneſtly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:41414:68"/>others, to perſevere in piety, preſſing to <hi>ſalvation,</hi> and waiting for the time when there ſhould be no more weeping or woe, no more pain or greif; no more fear or ſorrow; no more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, death, or danger: and ſhall I now give back, when God hath brought me to that time? ſhall I dread the diſcharge of evil, which I have all my days deſired and groaned for? or ſhall the <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> of this immunity, embitter mine expectation, or enjoyment of it; do I retain the ſence of evil, and can I deſire to return to it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain? have not the Paroxiſmes of a Feaver; the Fits of an Ague, of the Stone, or Collick, perplexed me, and made my ſtrength to fail? have not the threats of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane rage filled my ſoul with terror, and exceeding dread? have not mine apprehenſions of Gods wrath, and eternal woe, which my ſin hath deſerved, filled
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:41414:69"/>my heart with horror, my ſoul with fear and greif, and my bones with trembling? ſhall I now fear to be put into that eſtate, wherein all theſe evils ſhall end for ever? wherein I ſhall never more feel it, I ſhall never more fear it? Oh bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Eternity!</hi> annexed unto ſo <hi>great ſalvation!</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">Mine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance is eternal.</note> Death putteth my ſoul into the poſſeſſion of mine <hi>inheritance:</hi> the inheritance which Chriſt hath purchaſed for me; which God hath promiſed to me; the inheritance <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Saints;</hi> the <hi>inheritance of the Saints in light;</hi> the <hi>inheritance of an houſe in heaven;</hi> the <hi>inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the bleſſed manſions of God;</hi> the <hi>inheritance of a Kingdom;</hi> the <hi>Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God;</hi> in this <hi>inheritance</hi> I ſhall inherit the confluence of all honour and happineſs; in this <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance</hi> I ſhall ſit down a Co-heir with Jeſus Chriſt, the onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, the onely beloved Son of
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:41414:69"/>God: ſhall it greive me that this <hi>inheritance is eternal?</hi> is not <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> the Emphaſis, the excellency of this inheritance? my ſoul could never be ſo much raviſhed with the plenty, pleaſure, ſcituation, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, greatneſs, and glory of this mine <hi>inheritance,</hi> as it would be damped and deadned, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged and diſcomfited with the vanity, the tranſiency of the ſame: what a cutting conſideration would it be, to think there were but a poſſibility of a cutting off from this inheritance? or of my being caſt out of it, though but for a time? unto this <hi>inheritance</hi> I have been called by the glorious Goſpel; I have been ſealed by the bleſſed ſpirit of adoption; I have received in my ſelf the earneſt, the firſt fruits of this inheritance; I have been thereby encouraged in mine expectation, and enflamed in my deſire of a full poſſeſſion thereof; ſhall I now draw back, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:41414:70"/>mine <hi>inheritance,</hi> and the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of it, becauſe it is <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible and fadeth not away?</hi> becauſe it is eternal, without end? I have ever deemed and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the moſt rich and honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble inheritance on the earth, a pompous vanity; becauſe it is tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral and tranſient: Shall I now dread to enter into the poſſeſſion of that inheritance which is <hi>Real,</hi> becauſe <hi>Eternal?</hi> can I be ſo fooliſh as to deſire the worm of time ſhould eat into my fair eſtate, and make my flouriſhing <hi>inheritance</hi> to fade; I have all my days lived a child in nonage, longing for, and looking at, but kept out of mine inheritance, but I am now at age, I ſhall now become a man, a grown man, and enter upon and into mine eſtate: and this is my comfort, mine advantage, I ſhall abide a man, a perfect man for ever; the ſecond childehood of old age ſhall not overtake
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:41414:70"/>me, to deprive me of, or diſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitate me to enjoy this my <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly inheritance:</hi> Oh! how have I longed and laboured? how have I panted and prayed? how have I pleaded with God? how have I preſſed againſt the power of men and Devils, to get into the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this inheritance? now I am come to the door, ſhall I ſtand at the Threſhold? ſhall I dread to enter in, ſit down, and poſſeſs mine <hi>inheritance,</hi> becauſe it is <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal?</hi> will <hi>eternity</hi> be the burden of my heavenly eſtate?</p>
               <p>My ſoul! embrace death, the door, the dark entry which paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth thee into thine <hi>inheritance;</hi> proceed with joy, with courage; praiſe God for the <hi>eternity</hi> of thy future ſtate: is not this my ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, <hi>much better,</hi> becauſe <hi>more enduring</hi> then all my worldly goods? hath not the hope of this, made me content with the loſs, and to take joyfully the ſpoyling of thoſe?
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:41414:71"/>ſhall deſireable, delight, <hi>eternity</hi> diſmay my ſoul entring into the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of what I have ſo much e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed, ſo long expected? who would not exchange a Leaſe for life, for an <hi>inheritance to be enjoyed for ever?</hi> who would not part with all, to purchaſe, to poſſeſs ſuch an inheritance, a Royal, Heavenly, holy inheritance? and ſhall I not gladly breath out a <hi>dying life,</hi> to affix, and ſecure <hi>eternity</hi> to this mine <hi>inheritance?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3.
<note place="margin">Eternity is affixed to glory.</note> Death ſhall inveſt my ſoul with GLORY: Eternity muſt needs be the ſparkling luſtre of GLORY: mine <hi>Inheritance</hi> ſhall be a <hi>Glorious Inheritance;</hi> and ſo much more glorious by being eternal; mine inheritance is a palace, not a poor cottage; a manſion, not a move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Tent; a Kingdom, not a Country Village; an Heavenly, not an Earthly Kingdom; a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, not of men; and is not this a <hi>Glorious Inheritance?</hi>
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:41414:71"/>would not any man deſire to enjoy this for ever? Mine <hi>Inheritance,</hi> or eſtate in this world hath ever been poor, vile, and baſe; but my ſoul ſhall now paſs into <hi>Glory;</hi> and be inveſted with nothing but <hi>Glory;</hi> I ſhall when dead know by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, what I have long deſired, earneſtly prayed, and induſtriouſly laboured to know by the Spirit of wiſdom and underſtanding; <hi>(viz) What is the Riches of the glory of the inheritance of the Saints;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 1.18.</note> Now I have finiſhed my courſe on earth, I muſt go to Heaven; that I may there receive my Crown; may courſe here hath been the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual exerciſe of <hi>Grace;</hi> my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition hereafter muſt be the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant enjoyment of <hi>Glory:</hi> the <hi>place</hi> in which my ſoul muſt now abide; the <hi>buſineſs</hi> in which my ſoul ſhall be employed; the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany</hi> with which my ſoul ſhall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociate; and the <hi>qualities</hi> with which my ſoul ſhall be endowed,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:41414:72"/>are all <hi>glorious;</hi> theſe things are all tranſcendently <hi>glorious;</hi> I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but deſire they ſhould be; my ſoul cannot but leap for joy to think theſe <hi>glories</hi> are <hi>Eternal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The place in which my ſoul ſhall abide whilſt parted from;
<note place="margin">Heaven a glorious place.</note> yea when reunited to my body, is <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious,</hi> tranſcendently glorious; for it is <hi>Heaven:</hi> My conſtant future reſidence muſt be in the Court of Heaven; the <hi>Heaven of heavens;</hi> the <hi>third heavens;</hi> the <hi>Paradiſe of God;</hi> the place into which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Paul</hi> was taken up; in which he heard words not <hi>fit to be utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.2, 4.</note> and in which he ſaw <hi>Glories</hi> which he could not declare; the Court of the great King; the King of Saints; and the King of Kings; the peculiar Palace of Gods moſt <hi>glorious preſence;</hi> the holy, the heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 21.</note> the great Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, whoſe gates are pearl; whoſe pavement is gold; and whoſe foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations are precious ſtones; unto
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:41414:72"/>which the Kings of the earth do bring their glory and honour; in which there is no need of Sun, or Moon; for the glory of God doth lighten it; and the Lamb is the light thereof; into which there ſhall in no wiſe enter any thing which defileth, neither whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever worketh abomination, or maketh a lye; but they only whoſe names are written in the lambs book of life. My ſoul! Doſt thou linger to go unto, or doſt thou fear too long continuance in this place of glory? How have hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſences been raviſhed with the glory of the ſtructures raiſed by humane Art? how much have I admired the glorious work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip of God in the beſpangled firmament, the moſt curious ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melling the ſame with the Sun, Moon and Stars? and yet theſe are but dark ſhadows; moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect repreſentations of Heavens glory? and how far? how freely did
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:41414:73"/>the Queen of the South travel to ſee? with what raviſhing obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion did ſhe admire? how bleſſed did ſhe eſteem the men who did reſide in the ſtate of <hi>Solomons</hi> ſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures? wilt thou my ſoul flock to God and ſee, yea and fit down in the place prepared by the Lord, for his bleſſed ones, before the foundation of the world was laid? the glimpſe of this glorious King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, when the Lord Jeſus was trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figured, did ſo raviſh the three Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples, that they thought it was <hi>good to be there,</hi> and began to caſt how to build tabernacles,
<note place="margin">Matth. 17.2, 3, 4.</note> that they might there abide: Can I chuſe but long to ſee, and to ſet down my ſtation in the very place its ſelf where our Lord is ever in the truth and fulneſs of his glory? Come my ſoul! goe forth with joy, and thou ſhalt at once poſſeſs that place of <hi>glory,</hi> from which thou canſt no more remove, nor wilt deſire to do it: in which the <hi>eternity</hi> of thy
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:41414:73"/>reſidence, is and will be the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of thine injoyment; it would more grieve thee to <hi>go from,</hi> then not at firſt to have <hi>come</hi> to Heaven.</p>
               <p>The buſineſs in which my ſoul ſhall be employed in this <hi>glorious place,</hi> is alſo <hi>glorious:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the work is glorious.</note> for after death <hi>attendance on,</hi> and <hi>acclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of praiſe</hi> to God and Jeſus Chriſt, ſhall be the whole the only employment of mine immortal ſoul; <hi>beatifical viſion</hi> ſhall be its buſineſs: I ſhall then know God, as I am known of God; I have here beleived in him whom I have not ſeen, rejoyced with joy unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and full of glory: but ſhall then ſee him, in whom I have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leived; I ſhall ſee the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, not darkly, as in a glaſs, but face to face; how full? how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable? how glorious muſt needs be the joy which reflecteth from my ſence? how muſt it needs tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend that which was onely the reſult of faith? my ſoul when par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:41414:74"/>from my body ſhall (as the glorious Angels now do) miniſter continually in Gods immediate preſence; and behold his glory: Happy were <hi>Solomons</hi> ſervants who ſtood continually before him, and heard his wiſdom; Behold my ſoul! <hi>a greater then Solomon is here;</hi> thou ſhalt attend on, miniſter before, and hear the wiſdom, and behold the glory of the God of <hi>Solomons</hi> wiſdom, and glory.</p>
               <p>The ſouls which come out of great tribulation, are arayed in white robes, and advanced unto continual attendance on the throne of God; to ſerve him in his Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple night and day; where the whole of their buſineſs is, and for ever ſhall be to ſing Halelujahs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord; to admire the <hi>majeſty, wiſdom power</hi> &amp; <hi>goodneſs</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> to aſcribe <hi>wiſdom bleſſing, honour, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> unto God, for ever and ever; <hi>to him who ſitteth on the throne, and to the Lamb for euer:</hi> Gods
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:41414:74"/>ſervice was on earth my <hi>perfect free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom;</hi> it muſt needs be much more ſuch in Heaven: when I am once arrived at this eſtate of Glory, I ſhall be indeed, and for ever <hi>deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from all mine enemies; that I may ſerve him without fear all my days,</hi> which ſhall never end.</p>
               <p>Oh the honor of relation to ſuch a Maſter! oh the happineſs of em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment in ſuch buſineſs! <hi>It is a good thing to ſing praiſe unto our God; it is pleaſant, and praiſe is comely:</hi> Oh the glory of attendance on ſo glorious Majeſty! my ſoul, canſt thou wiſh thy time in a rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſo <hi>honourable;</hi> in an employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſo <hi>happy;</hi> in an attendance ſo <hi>glorious,</hi> were as the days of an hireling? God forbid: Loveſt thou the ſervice of thy God? ſhall the length of thy ſervitude diſmay thee? Wilt thou not conſent, yea deſire to be boared through the ear, that thou mayſt abide in this thy maſters ſervice for ever? Doſt thou
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:41414:75"/>long to turn thy faith into ſence? thy hope into fruition? thy prayers into praiſes? thine apprehenſions of God and Chriſt, into immediate attendance on them? is it poſſible thou ſhouldſt dread the <hi>eternity</hi> of this eſtate, thou ſo much, ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſireſt? art thou my ſoul ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of ſurfeiting with ſpiritual joyes? doſt thou not love and long to drink thy fill, to be drunk with the rivers of pleaſure which flow continually in Gods preſence? how have I mourned under the with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawings of Gods preſence! ſhall I now fear to approach his preſence, onely becauſe I ſhall never more be baniſh'd from his Court &amp; preſence?</p>
               <p>My ſoul! chear up; in Heaven, the frowns and frettings of thy Maſter, ſhall not make thee weary of waiting on him; his terrors ſhall no more make thee afraid, the ſplendor of his Majeſty ſhall not dazle thine eyes, nor diſcapacitate thy viſion of him; thy work ſhall
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:41414:75"/>not there be tyring; thy ſervice ſhall not then waſte thy ſtrength; wear thy cloaths; or dull thy ſpirits; that thou ſhouldſt wiſh for a return of time, wherein to take thine eaſe, obtain refreſhment, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue thine apparel: ſo eminent is this relation; ſo eaſie, ſo excellent is this employment; that the <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> hereof is mine exceeding, mine infinitely great advantage; I long to enter upon it; I ſhall never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to leave it; mine <hi>eternal</hi> enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it, is mine onely hope, my Glory.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Company</hi> with whom my ſoul parted from my body,
<note place="margin">In Heaven I ſhall have glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</note> ſhall aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate, is no leſs <hi>glorious</hi> then the place of my future reſidence; or the buſineſs of my future employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: when I dye I ſhall be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into, and entertained by the <hi>aſſemblies of the firſt born;</hi> whoſe names are written in heaven; and <hi>the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect;</hi> and the glorious <hi>Angels:</hi> thoſe ſhall
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:41414:76"/>henceforward be my <hi>companions for ever:</hi> Oh bleſſed company! who would not long to be with them? who would not gladly go to them? who can with any poſſible content think of parting from them? how fooliſhly loath am I to leave my friends on earth? yet I have not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed their company without a croſs; many of them have ſcorned me; many of them have ſlighted me; many of them have failed me; many of them have fallen out with me; many times they have provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked my paſſion, greived my ſoul, and vexed my ſpirit; all of them have one way or other given a check to my comfort and content in their ſociety. I now parting from them, ſhall paſs into, enjoy and never more be parted from much better, more deſireable, and more pleaſurable company.</p>
               <p>I ſhall now aſſociate with <hi>Angels,</hi> thoſe glorious creatures, the beauty of whoſe feet mortal eye can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:41414:76"/>look upon and live: thoſe holy <hi>ſpirits,</hi> who wait immediately on God; and with all power and ſpeed perform, the pleaſure of the moſt high; thoſe active ſpirits which are ſent of God, to miniſter unto the heirs of ſalvation, theſe are now attendant on me, though I ſee them not; they do me many good turnes, though I perceive it not; by them I am guarded in many dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; they keep me in all my ways; they pitch their tents about me; they do me much good, and yet I underſtand not their <hi>nature, office,</hi> or <hi>miniſtry;</hi> but now my Soul! they attend my death, to perform their laſt work to me; to receive thee, and carry thee into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſom, and to place thee in fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with themſelves: thou ſhalt thenceforward know them, their <hi>natures</hi> and <hi>offices;</hi> thou ſhalt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarly converſe with them, and not be affrighted by them; nor ſhalt thou be weary of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany;
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:41414:77"/>theſe will not ſcorn thee; theſe will not vex and grieve thee; but as faſt and faithful friends they will with freedom and fullneſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate themſelves unto thee; to the abundant increaſe of thy joy, which will be the more abundant by the eternity of thy abiding with them.</p>
               <p>My ſoul! though at death thou art taken from among men, and made a mate for Angels; yet thou ſhalt not onely converſe with theſe glorious creatures, <hi>different in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſeemingly above thee;</hi> thou ſhalt now alſo aſſociate with the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect: thou ſhalt ſit down with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac, and Jacob in the Kingdom of God:</hi> thou ſhalt now be placed under the Altar, among the ſouls of them who were ſlain for the <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of Jeſus:</hi> I have taken abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant pleaſure in the fellowſhip of the Saints on earth; yet there in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities have many times occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:41414:77"/>to me great vexations: Oh how pleaſurable will their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny be, now they are made perfect? I have had reverend thoughts of the Saints departed; the Fathers of Old; and the Martyrs of latter days: how precious do I account the memory of <hi>Adam, Enoch, Noah, Abraham, Iſaac, Jacob, Joſeph, David, Solomon, Iſaiah, Jeremiah, Ezekiel, Daniel, Zachariah, Peter, Paul, James, John, Ignatius, Polycarpus, Justin, Athanaſius, Wickliff, Hus, Luther, Calvin, Beza, Cranmer, Ridley, Latimer, Hooper, Glover, Rogers, Laurence, Bradford,</hi> with many others; of theſe I have onely heard, and read, I never yet knew them: but now my ſoul ſhall go to them; now my ſoul ſhall know them; it ſhall dwell in houſe, and be moſt fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly, moſt intimately acquainted with them; and not onely with theſe, but alſo with all the <hi>elect of God,</hi> whoſe names I have not
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:41414:78"/>yet heard of: this bleſſed ſociety ſhall ſo much increaſe the joy of my ſoul, as to make <hi>Eternity</hi> the height of its deſire, of its delight: who would not live for ever in ſo good a Neighbour-hood? it hath often greived me to part from good men on earth; I now lament that I muſt leave my godly friends on earth, and go to Heaven with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them; and yet this my loſs is made up by the enjoyment of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers as good, yea, much better: and I have an aſſurance, that thoſe I leave behind me, ſhall come to me; though I cannot come back to them: but Oh what an hell would it be, if time could cut me off from the bleſſed fellowſhip of theſe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified Saints and Angels! My ſoul! put out; paſs freely into the Ocean of Eternity; ſeeing thy voyage is made ſo comfortable, by ſailing in ſuch bleſſed company.
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ualities <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ow my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ul.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Qualities</hi> of my ſoul ſhall be ſuitable to this heavenly place,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:41414:78"/>work and company; for theſe alſo ſhall be <hi>Glorious:</hi> after death, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to God;</hi> and exact <hi>ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude to the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Joh: 3.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> ſhall be the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowment of my ſoul: <hi>we are now the Sons of God; it doth not yet ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear what we ſhall be; but we know, when he ſhall appear, we ſhall be like him; for we ſhall ſee him as he is:</hi> Oh bleſſed viſion, which transfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth its ſubject! the ſight of God and Chriſt by faith, as they are repreſented to us in the Goſpel, doth on earth begin that change in mans ſoul, which is compleated by the beatifical viſion of their real ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtency in themſelves: there can be no ſymmetry, without ſimilitude; no communion without conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; <hi>two cannot walk together except they be agreed;</hi> there can be no ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying apprehenſion of the object, but by a ſuitable organ; <hi>Like to like,</hi> is the formal reaſon of all true, and full content; they that will ſee God and live, muſt be
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:41414:79"/>
                  <hi>holy, as God is holy;</hi> and <hi>perfect, as God is perfect.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My ſoul! paſſing into immediate communion with, muſt be made <hi>conformable to God:</hi> his image ſtamped on man in his creation, was the principle and capacity of communion with God: this defaced by ſin, man was driven, and hath been kept at a diſtance from God; but this ſhall be now reſtored to, and compleated in my ſoul; that it may return into conſtant com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God: all that diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and diſproportion which ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred God dreadful and deſtructive to my being; and therefore deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red mine approach to him; ſhall at death be utterly and for ever diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged: My ſoul ſhall then indeed be <hi>holy as God is holy;</hi> and <hi>perfect as God is perfect:</hi> it ſhall not only have <hi>perfect qualities,</hi> the principles of union; but alſo thoſe degrees of perfection which ſhall capacitate it for full communion with my God,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:41414:79"/>Chriſt, and his Holy Angels, and glorified Saints; even the utmoſt degree of perfection ſuch a creature is capable of; and an eſtate of ſo glorious communion doth call for, and require.</p>
               <p>The faculties of my ſoul ſhall be enlarged, unto the perfection of <hi>knowledge and affection:</hi> I ſhall after death, be able to pry into the deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt myſteries of <hi>mans fall, and ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> of the glorious unconceivable ſubſiſtency of the <hi>Trinity in unity, three perſons, in one undivided eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence;</hi> of the miraculous hypoſtatical union of the <hi>two natures, God and Man in one perſon;</hi> of the bleſſed <hi>incarnation,</hi> and whole work of <hi>redemption,</hi> which is nothing but a <hi>Cabal of myſteries:</hi> I ſhall then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend incomprehenſible glory, without the leaſt defect, doubting, or difficulty; I now know but in part, I ſhall then know perfectly; knowledge, righteouſneſs, and true holineſs, thoſe parts of the new
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:41414:80"/>man, ſhall then attain to a perfect virile ſtrength and ſtature; the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine nature whereof I here partake ſhall then be in me compleat: I ſhall then know all things fully, and with <hi>full content:</hi> mine affections will then moſt freely cloſe with, and take full complacency in thoſe glorious ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, mine underſtanding ſhall then know &amp; comprehend my: mind ſhall not know more of God and Chriſt, then my ſoul ſhall admire, mine af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections imbrace, unto the fulneſs of my comfort, forcing out the loud halelujahs, and acclamations of joy and thankſgiving to God for ever: the imbicility of the natural man, which could not; the enmity of the natural man, which would not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern and ſavour the things of God, ſhall now be diſcharged, deſtroyed for ever; for now the natural man it ſelf, ſhall expire and ceaſe to be.</p>
               <p>Such ſhall be the changed eſtate, <hi>qualitie</hi> and endowments of my ſoul, that the things which were to
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:41414:80"/>it tiring, dulling &amp; difficult, becauſe <hi>ſupernatural;</hi> irkſom, greivous and hateful, becauſe <hi>contranatural;</hi> ſhall become eaſie and encouraging; lovely, acceptable and delightful, becauſe <hi>connatural;</hi> the very, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and only element in which my ſoul can live and enjoy it ſelf: in this reſpect nothing could be ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maying, afflicting and tormenting to my ſoul, as <hi>interruption, intermiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> or <hi>expiration</hi> of enjoyment by the return of time; Oh folly! to dread Eternity, which muſt exiſt in the exerciſe and enjoyment of theſe glorious qualities of my ſoul! the diſparity and diſproportion which keepeth my God and me at a diſtance, ſhall now be diſcharged, and quite removed; can I deſire the time in which they ſhall again re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn upon me? hath not the loſs of Gods image in me, and thereby the loſs of his preſence with me, coſt me dear enough already? I cannot enjoy God for ever, unleſs I be
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:41414:81"/>like God for ever; my perfect pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to God muſt fit me for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect poſſeſſion of God: welcome then <hi>Eternity in conformity to God,</hi> my only capacity of <hi>eternal commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4.
<note place="margin">My future life is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal.</note> Though I dye, <hi>I ſhall dye but once;</hi> my death ſhall be mine en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into <hi>life;</hi> and my <hi>life ſhall be eternal;</hi> the <hi>ſecond death</hi> ſhall have no power on me: ſeeing I muſt once dye, oh how happy am I that I do not live to dye the <hi>ſecond death!</hi> the firſt death <hi>divideth my ſoul from my body;</hi> but the ſecond death would have <hi>dividid my ſoul and body from God, and that for ever:</hi> but this death ſhall not befall me; for <hi>there is no condemnation to them who are in Chriſt Jeſus;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.1.</note> the Lord hath <hi>juſtified me;</hi> who ſhall <hi>condemn me?</hi> he hath delivered me from the dread of the <hi>firſt,</hi> by redeeming me from the power of the <hi>ſecond death:</hi> I may be of good comfort, <hi>I ſhall not dye, but live;</hi> I ſhall live in death; I ſhall paſs
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:41414:81"/>through <hi>death to life;</hi> and whilſt <hi>life</hi> is the ſubject, who would not deſire to have <hi>eternity</hi> the adjunct? My ſoul, canſt thou chuſe but joy, to know that thy life is <hi>eternal life?</hi> do I dread to die, and tremble to think of <hi>Eternity in life?</hi> O ſtrange con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction! the reſult of a weak faith, and of a clouded reaſon: na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath taught me to deſire and endeavour the preſervation, and if it were poſſible the perpetuation of my natural, ſinful, ſorrowful life; ſhall not grace much more make me to rejoyce, that my holy, happy life <hi>endureth for ever?</hi> that I ſhall <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally live in the ſalvation of God,</hi> to enjoy mine <hi>inheritance</hi> among <hi>the Saints and Angels in light;</hi> to <hi>attend on, contemplate,</hi> and <hi>have communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with God and Chriſt?</hi> were not <hi>eternal life</hi> affixed to theſe enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, what would they avail me? what? ſhould I delight to tantalize in the <hi>waters of life? Eternity</hi> ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted, I do but catch at the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:41414:82"/>I cannot hold; I do fall under <hi>Moſes</hi> his chance, <hi>Moſes</hi> his curſe; he led <hi>Iſrael</hi> to the banks of <hi>Jordan,</hi> to the borders of <hi>Canaan;</hi> he went up to mount <hi>Nebo,</hi> and ſaw the goodly land, but he entred not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it; he enjoyed it not; he died in the mountain: I have preached <hi>Eternal life;</hi> I have perſwaded men to purſue it, to preſs after it; I have led them to the brink of the grave, and am ready to lye down and dye, &amp; now I dread the <hi>eternal life</hi> that attendeth me. O my folly! but bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be God he hath not been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked; he will not be by me per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to blot my name out of the <hi>book of life;</hi> but having purpoſed, purchaſed for me, and promiſed to me <hi>ſalvation,</hi> an <hi>inheritance,</hi> an <hi>eſtate of glory;</hi> he hath ſecured me my <hi>life</hi> in, and unto the poſſeſſion thereof; and made <hi>eternity</hi> the bleſſed, inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable property of them all.</p>
               <p>My ſoul! where art thou? what? art thou lanched into? loſt in <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi>
                  <pb n="147" facs="tcp:41414:82"/>before out of my body? return; recover thy ſelf <hi>before thou go hence, and be no more ſeen;</hi> look back on thine own thoughts; ſurvey the land which the proſpect of thy faith hath deſcried in the ocean of <hi>eternity:</hi> O the immenſity! O the depth of <hi>eternity!</hi> this is an aſtoniſhing ocean; an amazing ſea; whilſt I ſtand on the banks of a temporal life, how do I tremble to look upon <hi>eternity,</hi> in its abſtracted nature? but ſtay my ſoul! let us be wiſe; let my faith follow this flood; and deliberately obſerve how it ſtreams it ſelf in the Paradiſe of God; into <hi>eternal ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation;</hi> oh wonderful! <hi>Eternal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance;</hi> O this is deſirable! how do I long for it? <hi>Eternal glory;</hi> that is delightful! the rayes thereof ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh my heart: And <hi>Eternal life;</hi> O the emphaſis, the excellency of all the reſt! ſhall I dread to ſhoot this gulph of death? ſhall I fear to lanch out into the depth of this <hi>eternity?</hi> can theſe bleſſed, deſired, never
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:41414:83"/>enough deſired things be abſtracted from? be enjoyed without <hi>eternity?</hi> if they could, would they be ſo good? would they be ſuch things? is not <hi>eternity</hi> the very formality of them? is not <hi>eternity</hi> that maſſie ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, affixed to the <hi>exceeding weight of glory,</hi> which counterpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, weigheth down, and witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the <hi>levity</hi> of thoſe afflictions which we now ſuffer for a moment? <hi>Eternity</hi> is the <hi>ſting</hi> of <hi>ſorrow,</hi> but the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of <hi>joy;</hi> the <hi>horror</hi> of <hi>damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> but the <hi>honour</hi> of <hi>ſalvation;</hi> the <hi>dread,</hi> the <hi>dolor</hi> of <hi>the reprobate:</hi> but the <hi>deſire</hi> &amp; <hi>delight</hi> of <hi>the Elect;</hi> the <hi>plague,</hi> the <hi>ſting</hi> of the <hi>gnawing worm,</hi> and tormenting not conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fire; but the <hi>pleaſure,</hi> the <hi>luſtre</hi> of the <hi>wedding garment,</hi> and of the cooling, refreſhing ſtreams of the <hi>waters of life:</hi> My ſoul; Chriſt my Savior hath redeemed me from the one, and ſealed me to the other of theſe conditions; fear not therefore to go out of this body, to paſs
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:41414:83"/>through this red Sea; this dark, dreadful, diſmaying gulf into the Ocean of thine <hi>Eternity;</hi> remember, conſider thy Lord long ſince decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>ſtrait is the gate, and narow is the way which leadeth unto life:</hi> I will by Gods grace ſtoop at this <hi>ſtrait gate;</hi> I will preſs through this <hi>narrow way;</hi> ſeeing <hi>life,</hi> ſo rich, ſo glorious, ſo bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed life is the end thereof; to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed for ever.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The Concluſion.</head>
               <p>§. MOſt bleſſed Jeſus! thou art the Lord of life and glory: of thine own good will in compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and pity to loſt man; thou didſt leave the delights of Heaven, and of thy fathers boſome; and waſt cloathed with mans mortal nature.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt ſubjected thy ſelf to death; to the moſt violent, ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and curſed death; that thou mighteſt ſweeten and ſanctifie this cup; in which all thine elect and Saints muſt pledge thee: thou haſt taſted death for all men.</p>
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:41414:84"/>
               <p>Thou having felt the ſting, and encountred the ſtrength of death; didſt conquer and triumph over the grave: thou haſt gotten; thou haſt given all that beleive in thee the victory over death: thou art in thy Church, and to thy Saints, the firſt fruits from the dead; thy glorious reſurrection is our pledge, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance that we ſhall not be always held under the power and domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of death; but that we ſhall be raiſed up, to raign with <hi>thee</hi> for <hi>ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. I thy weak and worthleſs ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, am under the expectation of death; and (if thou reſtrain not the wrath that is in man) it may be a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent, and ſhameful death: under the dread hereof, I look unto, and deſire to encourage my ſelf in thee, <hi>the captain of my ſalvation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Be not far from me my God, and my Saviour, in this hour of my tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation; but let thy grace ſupport me under the ſtroak; and ſave me from the ſting of death; ſtrengthen
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:41414:84"/>my faith unto the full apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; due application of thy death, and reſurrection; to the curbing of my paſſions, and check of my fears; that I may willingly, cheerfully, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low thee through the <hi>vale of the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of death:</hi> O be my God! my <hi>God</hi> and my <hi>Guide</hi> unto, &amp; under death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>§. Death is natural to man;</hi> common to all men; but its nature is changed unto ſome, and but to ſome of the ſons of men; this dreadful Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner of thy vengeance on the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; is but a grim meſſenger to fetch thy children home; this thy Sheriff, executing Malectours; putteth the heirs of ſalvation into the poſſeſſion of that inheritance thou haſt pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed for them, and appointed to them; the wicked dye, when thy friends do but ſleep and reſt in their beds.</p>
               <p>Be pleaſed O my Redeemer! to know me, and make me know my ſelf to be one of that number, to whom the nature of death is chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:41414:85"/>to whom it may not, it cannot be apprehended, or appear ſo dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful: evidence and cleer up to my ſoul and conſcience, that real, ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural change of quality in my ſelf; which may convince me of, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure unto me, the contranatural change of the nature and quality of death, to and upon me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>§.</hi> Union with thy glorious ſelf, can only ſecure againſt the ſting, and encourage under &amp; againſt the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying apprehenſion of the ſtroak of death: unite me O Lord unto thy ſelf! communicate to me thy grace; that only evidence of my union with thee; that aſſurance, that only; that full aſſurance that death ſhall not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide between thee and me; death ſhall not ſeperate my ſoul from <hi>thee;</hi> death ſhall not ſeperate my body from thee; but my duſt ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded by thee; my death ſhall be precious in thy ſight: make (O my God) the graces of thine holy ſpirit ſo legible in me; that I may thereby
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:41414:85"/>make my calling and election ſure; and read readily that name that none can read but he who hath it: and that I may be certainly reſolved in my ſelf that my name was written in thy book of life, before the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of the world was laid.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>§.</hi> Thy grace (O Lord) hath been extended to me; make me to ſee it; teach me ſeriouſly to reflect it, unto thy praiſe and the encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my ſoul under, and againſt the terrors of the dread of death.</p>
               <p>I am through thy grace and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant mercy, called by the name; I have been born within the pale of thy Church, and under the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of thy ſalvation: I was dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to thee and thy ſervice as ſoon as I was born; thy covenant was then ſet on my fleſh by baptiſm, and I now bear it on my fleſh; I dare not with prophane <hi>Eſau,</hi> deſpiſe this my birth-right; but muſt, and by thy grace I will rejoyce, that I pertake of the fatneſs of the Olive;
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:41414:86"/>and that I am a branch from an holy root, ſanctified by, and unto God.</p>
               <p>Thou didſt bleſs me (O Lord) with Chriſtian nurture and educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; I have known thy word from my childhood; thou haſt ſeaſoned me with, and ſanctified me by thy truth; thy word is truth; it hath been the delight of my ſoul; and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of my life and faith.</p>
               <p>Thy ſpirit hath been and is in me, the ſpirit of conviction and of bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, by it I ſee the finfulneſs of ſin; and poſſeſs with grief &amp; ſhame the iniquities of my youth, and the evil of my ways and doings: it luſteth againſt my fleſh; and draweth, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth my mind to ſerve the Law of God, when my fleſh is forced to ſerve the Law of ſin.</p>
               <p>Thy glorious Goſpel, thy gracious ſpirit (O Lord) hath convinced me of, and affected my ſoul with mine own guilt; thy fathers wrath and juſtice, and the ſalvation wrought out by thee, and by thee alone; I
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:41414:86"/>do <hi>beleive</hi> there is no <hi>name</hi> by which men can be ſaved, but thy name moſt bleſſed Jeſus; thou art the true <hi>Meſſiah;</hi> the only Mediator between God and man; the all-ſufficient Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of all that come unto thee: unto thee (O Lord) I come, <hi>weary and heavy loaden with my ſin;</hi> Oh give me eaſie! <hi>preſſed</hi> with a dread of thy fathers wrath; plead my cauſe, ſatisfie for me his offended juſtice; be the propitiation for my ſins: <hi>oppreſſed with my luſts;</hi> Oh ſave me from my ſin; ſubdue corruptions in me; change my nature; be to me a perfect Saviour, for to thee I run, on thee I relye; thee I embrace with all my ſoul, to be my Lord and my King; refuſe, reject me not, O God of my ſalvation.</p>
               <p>I have reſigned up my whole man to thy moſt holy word and will; and deſire to <hi>walk</hi> in thy moſt <hi>holy ways:</hi> thy love ſhed abroad in my heart, hath enflamed me with a love to thy name, to thine ordinances, thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:41414:87"/>and thine houſe; <hi>the zeal of thy houſe hath conſumed me; I have through thy ſpirit, embraced, eſteemed thy truth in the love thereof;</hi> and thy people for the truths ſake which is in them.</p>
               <p>For thy ſake I have denied all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward comforts; I have taken up my croſs and followed thee; Conſider, remember (O Lord) my preſent bonds; for <hi>thy ſake I am killed all the day long;</hi> I am accounted as a Sheep for the ſlaughter; the reproaches of them who reproach thee, are fallen upon me; all this is come upon me, yet have I not departed from thee; nor dealt falſly in the Covenant, in which thy glory is concerned.</p>
               <p>§. Theſe things O Lord I do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect, not as matters of merit in me; or as engagements on thy juſtice to do me good; for I well know they are not mine own; and if they were, and were perfect; yet, I muſt (when I have done the beſt I can) acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, I am an unprofitable ſervant;
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:41414:87"/>all I can do is due to thee; the beſt of my actions are but the debt I ow thee: but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, my beſt actions are full of ſin, my righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs is as a filthy rag, &amp; a menſtruous garment, which needeth thy propitiation and thy fathers pardon; and muſt be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumed by the incenſe, which is on the cenſer, in the right hand of thee my high Prieſt. Yet O my Savour! I reveiw theſe things in me, as the effects of thy grace to me; &amp; of thy ſpirit in me, and as infallible evidences of thine union to me; for fleſh and blood could not reveal, nor work theſe things in me: by thy grace ſanctifying my nature, my ſoul is and ſhall be ſaved: ô refuſe me not! deny me not to be thine! O let thy ſpirit of adoption ſeal up my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to thee! and mine intereſt in thee! let me not remain in the dark, or be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in a matter of ſo great concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to me, clear up to me by certain pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, the truth, the realty of mine inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perable union with thee! elſe I am undon, &amp; have ſaid nothing to my ſoul, in all that I have ſaid againſt the dread of death.</p>
               <p>§. Grant unto me O Lord; the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of all my ſins; the ſence of the guilt thereof doth ſting my ſoul; under the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of mine approaching death: Whatſoever doth befall me in this life, I
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:41414:88"/>beſeech thee ſuffer me not to dye in my ſin; Oh convince me of, humble me for, and turn me from all iniquity, and every reigning luſt: but graciouſly caſt it behind thy back; blot it out of thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, that in the day it is ſought for it may not be found againſt me: ſin hath paſſed on me, and death by ſin; but deliver me, O my Saviour, from falling by &amp; under the ſecond death, from which there is no poſſibility of redemption.</p>
               <p>Secure unto my ſoul thy ſufferings, as the full ranſom of my ſoul, and the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to thy fathers law, and juſtice for mine offences; and for my many great trangreſſions, ſo ſhall I be able to meet death with boldneſs; I ſhall then inſult over that King of terrors, with on <hi>O death where is thy ſting, O grave where is thy vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory;</hi> I ſhall then triumph over death; and him who hath the power of death, the Devil: If my heart deceive me not, I would not ſin that grace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hould abound; but now (bleſſed Saviour) that I have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, I do, I dare not but earneſtly beg thy grace may abound, that I may in my death through the pardon of ſin, ſing unto thy praiſe, <hi>thanks be unto God who hath given met he victory through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. O thou the only high Prieſt of my
<pb facs="tcp:41414:88"/>profeſſion! thou canſt be touched with mine infirmities; thou knoweſt the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er the prevalency of my natural paſſions, under the apprehenſions of mine approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching death: thou ever liveſt to make in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion for me: graciouſly rebuke my paſſions, reſtrain my fears, revive my faith, renew my hope, and eſtabliſh my heart under and againſt all thoſe amazing, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighting apprehenfions of death, which nature dot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conceive, ſence doth dictate, or Satan doth ſuggeſt unto my dread. Compaſſionately grant me the comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſupports of thy preſence, grace and ſpirit, whilſt <hi>I walk in the vale of the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of death;</hi> that I may with all patience and meekneſs lie down, and receive that ſtroak of death which I cannot avoid, and yet cannot be willing to receive. That I may with ſubmiſſion drink that bitter cup thou putteſt into my hand, concerning which; my nature not corrupted with ſin could not but pray, <hi>Father if it be poſſible let this cup paſs from me:</hi> give me an heart groaning to be clothed on, with my houſe from heaven; whilſt I cannot deſire to be uncloathed of this earthly tabernacle: and ſeeing my preſence in the fleſh, is mine ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence from thee O Lord; perſwade me to be willing to be diſſolved, that I may be with thee, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is beſt of all.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:41414:89"/>
               <p>§. As a man I cannot deſire, I cannot but fear to die: be pleaſed (O my Savior) to convince me of, and afflict me with, the happy ſequels of my death; that the ſence thereof may make me contrary to the power &amp; property of my nature deſirous to die: let not the dread of death drive me to accept on ſinful terms the deliverance from the moſt violent, and ſhameful ſtroak thereof: enable me to live, the laſt breath of this my dying life in the ways of thy truth and holineſs, to the praiſe of thy grace, and in this laſt act to play the man, couragiouſly evidencing my ſelf affected with a clear ſence that all the evils of <hi>death</hi> are diſcharged, and aſſured that I am uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to thee <hi>who art the reſurrection and the life;</hi> through whom, though I die, I ſhall live again; and having fought the good fight of faith, and finiſhed my courſe of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; I ſhall eſcape the curſe of death, and be received into eternal life and glory with thy ſelf, thy bleſſed Saints and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels for ever; guide me all my days by thy counſel, and at laſt receive me into thy glory: Into thy hands I commit my ſpirit, it is thine own thou haſt redeemed it, and thou wilt keep it until thy glorious ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, bleſſed Jeſus, my Lord and my Redeemer. <hi>Amen, Amen, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:41414:89"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
